Thank you for your participation
謝謝大家的參與
The hot weather of the summer vacation
那暑假這個很熱的天氣
Then everyone made a special trip to come over and was very touched
然後大家還專程過來非常感動
that mainly i think
那主要我想
Of course, you may be interested in this topic
當然大家可能有興趣的就是這個題目
is we put
就是我們把
It is the Laceup key
就是Laceup鍵
Laceup button
Laceup鍵
Anyway
Anyway
well that's mainly this
好那主要是這個
How can we in Taipei follow
我們台北都會怎麼會跟
Pompeii linked together
蓬佩古城連結在一起
Well, in fact, especially in recent years
那其實這個特別最近幾年來
We do a lot of work on the mainland site
我們在大陸網站做的很多工作
Of course, this world happens to have
那當然世界上剛好這個有
Pompeii film in 2014 also
蓬佩古城的電影在2014也
also played
也播放的
So the whole world is especially Taiwanese
所以全世界特別台灣人特別的
Notice
注意
In fact, there are actually many topics for such a topic.
那其實給這麼個題目其實很多
My colleagues or some friends say that my topic is too sensational
我的同事或者一些朋友都說我這個題目太聳動了
So you give this title
所以你給這個題目就是
Just to trick everyone
就是要騙大家來的
Actually this topic is not
其實這個題目不是
I shouldn't have given it to you
應該不是我給的啦
Conversely, because I did work on the Continental War
反過來講是因為我做了大陸火戰的工作
So I go to many places, no matter assisting speeches or popular science speeches
所以到很多地方不管協助演講或者科普演講
In fact, after most of the speeches, people will come to me and ask me
其實每次演講完大部分就會有人跑來問我
Will Taipei become Pompeii?
說台北會不會變成龐貝古城
So this is something that a lot of people care about
所以這是代表很多人關心的
then i hope today this
那我希望今天這個
more than an hour of these materials
超過一個小時的這些資料
After sharing with you, I think everyone will have the answer
跟大家分享完以後我想大家就會有答案的
This very clear answer must be presented
這個很清楚的答案一定就可以呈現出來
especially in recent months
那特別最近幾個月
Last one or two years
最近一兩年
we'll start with this
我們就從這個開始講
At the end of last year, the Legislative Yuan
這個立法院在去年底
volcanic disaster
就把火山災害
Natural disasters like earthquakes, typhoons, floods, etc.
變成台灣的像地震、颱風、淹水之類的天然災害
add volcanic disaster
把火山災害加進去
But everyone knows this is a new thing
但是大家就知道這個是一個新的東西
the past was never
過去是從來沒有的
That's because the Legislative Yuan passed this amendment
那因為立法院通過了這個修法
Therefore, the Executive Yuan and local governments have taken many related actions.
所以行政院跟地方政府都有很多的相關的動作
that's especially taipei
那特別是台北
The volcanic disaster that Taipei also practiced at the end of March this year
台北在今年的3月底也演習的火山災害
Especially for the residents of Beitou and Tianmu under Yangming Mountain
特別對於這個陽明山底下的這些北投、天母這些居民
let them know in case of volcanic activity
讓他們知道說萬一有火山活動的時候
how to deal with
應該怎麼去應對
Because in the history of mankind we Taiwan
因為在人類歷史上我們台灣
but no volcanic disaster
卻沒有火山的災害
The Philippines, Japan, Indonesia around us
我們周遭的菲律賓、日本、印尼
In fact, there are volcanic disasters at both ends of the three days
其實三天兩頭都有火山災害
Both their people and the government have some ideas about how to deal with it
他們的民眾跟政府都比較有些觀念怎麼去面對它
But Taiwan is really strange
但是台灣是真的很陌生
So hopefully we know more about the hazards of this volcano
所以希望我們對這個火山的災害有更多的了解
especially in recent months
那特別最近幾個月
Volcanoes this May in Hawaii
這個夏威夷的五月的火山
The dragon smoke flow is on the road
這個龍煙流就到的這個公路上面
Everyone knows that Dragon Mist
那龍煙流大家都知道
It's very hot and very scary
這是非常高溫非常可怕的
Anything that touches it will be completely destroyed.
那碰到什麼就完全就破壞了
Then if you go to Google and read a lot of reports like this
那你如果去Google上面看蠻多的這種報導
Whether it's a direct dragon smoke stream
那不管是直接的龍煙流
Or some breathing or toxic gas
或者一些呼吸的或者有毒氣體啊
There are actually many kinds
種種的其實非常多
In fact, here I would like to point out the following
那在這裡其實我特別要指出下面這個
This time, the eruption of this volcano
這個這一次這個火山的噴發
Caused a 6.9 earthquake
引發了一個6.9的地震
That's actually science
那這個其實是科學界
Or quite a lot of people are quite curious
或者蠻多民眾都蠻好奇
Do volcanoes cause earthquakes?
就是火山會不會引發地震
Not only this time in Hawaii
那夏威夷不只這一次
The volcanic eruption in 1975
在1975年那一次的火山噴發
Also triggered a larger 7.1 earthquake
也引發了一個更大7.1的地震
So what's the point of this?
那這個有什麼意義呢?
In fact, if you are interested in earth science or Taiwan
其實如果你對地球科學或對台灣
If there are some concepts of these geology in northern Taiwan
北台灣的這些地質有一些概念的話
In fact, you will think of what is next to the volcano on the mainland
其實就會聯想到大陸火山旁邊就有什麼
We actually have quite a few foothill faults that seismologists worry about
我們其實還蠻多地震學家擔心的山腳斷層
Then someone talked about volcanic activity
那也有人講說火山活動
Could it be something like the event that triggered the Foothill Fault?
會不會像引發山腳斷層的活動
The foothills fault in the evaluation of experts and scholars
那山腳斷層在專家學者的評估
If this dislocation of the entire fault at the foot of the mountain
如果它整個山腳斷層的這個錯動的話
The earthquake that is likely to be triggered is about 6.5 to 6.6
很可能引發的地震大概也是6.5 6.6左右
Although not very big compared with this
雖然不是很大跟這個比
But it's on the fringe of metropolis Taipei
但是它就在台北都會的邊緣
In fact, according to the evaluation of the International Earthquake Company Center
那其實據這個國際地震公司中心的做一些評估
If the fault at the foot of the mountain is active
如果山腳斷層活動的話
Thousands of houses in Taipei may collapse
台北可能有幾千棟的房子會倒
Of course thousands of lives were lost
那當然也有幾千個人命的損失
it's potentially dangerous
這是潛在的危險
Of course, this is the relationship between outer volcanoes and earthquakes
當然這是外外火山跟地震之間的關係
volcanoes cause earthquakes
火山會引發地震
Earthquakes trigger volcanoes
地震會引發火山
But it doesn't have to be a matter of incentives
但是不是一定它是有激勵的問題
in some cases there will be
在有些情況上會有
The summer fish activity in May
那5月夏貨魚活動
volcanic activity
火山活動
On June 2nd, Gualimara in Central and South America
6月2號這個中南美的瓜利馬拉
This is also the scene of the volcano
這個也是火山的景象
There can be these lava flows, debris flows, mudflows
可以有這些熔岩流 碎屑流 泥流
Then look at the volcanic eruption of summer fish
那你看夏貨魚的火山噴發
from the past few decades
從過去的幾十年來
hardly a single life was lost
幾乎沒有一個人命的損失
But compared to Central and South America
但是相對於中南美
Look at this a volcanic eruption
你看這個一個火山噴發
dozens of people died
就有幾十個人死亡
hundreds of people missing
幾百個人失蹤
Most of that believed to be missing
那大部分相信失蹤
Roughly equal to the number of deaths
大概等於是死亡的人數
then you can see
那你可以看到
This Central and South American and summer fish
這個中南美跟夏貨魚
why such a big difference
為什麼這麼大的差別
In addition to the difference in volcanic characteristics
除了火山特性的不一樣
actually very important very important what is
其實很重要很重要是什麼
This summer fish has done a lot of work
這個夏貨魚做了很多工作
Japan has done a lot
日本做了很多工作
Volcanoes like Japan are often erupting
像日本的火山也是常常在噴發
But the threat to human life
但是其實人命的威脅
really very few
真的是少之又少
That
那
Like this June, Sakurajima Volcano is erupting
就像這個6月中,櫻島火山在噴發
Of course, this dragon is flowing, because Sakurajima is across the sea
當然這個龍煙流,因為櫻島隔個海
So there is actually no direct dragon smoke flow, broken hole flow, or threat to this city.
所以到這個都市其實是沒有直接的龍煙流,碎穴流,威脅
But volcanic ash is actually causing a lot of trouble, too.
但是火山灰其實也造成很大的麻煩
Then this Bali Island, Bali Island in Indonesia
那這個巴黎島的,印尼的巴黎島
This is also the last volcanic activity at the end of June
這個也是最近6月底火山又活動
Then some of the things that caused the tourist crowds
然後造成的旅遊的人潮的一些丹物
Well, I'm actually going to tell a little story about this.
那其實這個我就要講一個小小的故事
It's the end of June this year
這是今年的6月底
In fact, Agong Volcano was in October last year
那其實阿公火山在去年的10月
If everyone has an impression, he also sprayed it once
如果大家有印象的時候,他也噴過一次
Then this was two months before the eruption of Agong Volcano
那這個就當初在阿公火山要噴發的前兩個月
One day I arrived at the office at 8 o'clock in the morning
有一天我早上8點多到辦公室
I got a call from this certain reporter, a reporter from the radio station.
就接了一通這個某個記者,電台的記者
He called and said, Teacher Lin, hello, I'm Momo reporter
他打電話來說 林老師你好 我是摩摩記者
Who, who, actually, I can't remember
誰誰誰 其實我也記不得了
Well, it's really because of too many reporters.
好 這真的因為太多記者
Then I said yes yes I remembered
然後我就說 是是是我記的
He said let me ask you a question
他說我請教你一個問題
I said I thought there was another news
我說我以為又有什麼新聞
He said no no it was a personal accident
他說沒有沒有 這是個人的失事
The reason is that he is going to Paris Island
原因是他要去巴黎島
He's celebrating his 25th birthday
他要慶生 25歲那種
Because those friends are going to Paris Island to play
因為那幾個朋友要去巴黎島玩
As a result, when he was going
結果他要去的時候
Paris Island announced that the volcano had started quasi-motion
巴黎島就宣佈說火山開始純准運動
Then he called me and asked me if I wanted to go
然後他就打電話問我說要不要去
then i will talk to him
那我就跟他講說
This Indonesian survey
這個印尼的調查
Because I don't have the data
因為資料我也沒在手上
I don't understand very clearly
我也不是了解很清楚
but i told him
但是我跟他講說
if you are not in such a hurry
你如果不是那麼急的話
you may wait a little while
你可能稍微等一下讓
After Indonesia or the official announcement
這個印尼或者官方有一些宣佈以後
then you have to judge
那你再來做判斷
Then he probably listened to me
那他就大概聽了我的話
just two months
就過了兩個月
another morning
一個早上又來了
he called again
他又打電話
I'm Mongolian reporter
我是蒙古爾記者
He said sorry for me now
他說對不起我現在
Now at Zhongzheng Airport
現在在中正機場
the night before
前一天晚上
waited for two months
等了兩個月
Volcano finally erupts to the surface
火山終於噴發到地表
He said, should I go?
他就說那我該不該去
really two months
真正兩個月的時間
I said you are amazing
我說你還真厲害
The flight was delayed just in time for the volcanic eruption
這個機票一延的剛好就是火山噴發的時候
Then I told him that you might go
那我跟他講說你去可能
Maybe there will be a delay at the airport like this
也許會就這樣機場會有Delay啊
But because
但是因為
The one that erupted from Grandpa Volcano
阿公火山噴的那個跟
This Paris Island tourist place is about 60 kilometers away
這個巴黎島旅遊地方大概60公里
Maybe the volcano will have some impact on the airport
可能火山會對機場有些影響
But at least the safety of your life should be nothing
但是至少你的這個生命的安全應該沒有什麼
scruples
顧忌
so he went
所以他就去了
so what does this represent
所以這個代表什麼
In fact, the volcano does not come instantly
其實火山不是瞬間就會來的
unlike an earthquake
不像地震
We can't predict earthquakes yet.
地震其實我們現在還沒有辦法預測
when will you come
哪時候要來
no one can tell
誰都說不上來
But volcanoes basically
但是火山基本上
like just said
就像剛剛講的
this japan america
這個日本美國
or these
或者這些
They can actually warn you by doing some observation techniques
他們做一些觀術其實都可以跟你警告
He started moving purely
他開始純准移動了
You may have to prepare or do something
你可能要做準備或者要有什麼動作
So overall
所以整個來講
In fact, the simplest way is to say
其實最簡單來講就是說
You may well imagine that
大家很可能會想像的就是說
this is our taipei
這是我們的台北
this is 101
這是101
This is me climbing to the top of the Nine-Five Peak
這是我爬到那個九五峰上面
took a photo
拍了一張照片
Then I put this
然後我把這個
The ancient city of Pompeii covered the Seven Star Mountain
龐貝古城就把七星山把它蓋住
will it be like this
會不會這樣
It's something that many people imagine
這是很多人想像的一個事情
then we want to talk today
那我們今天就希望來談談
Pompeii and Taipei
龐貝跟台北
or this
或者是這個
The Great Looming Volcano
這個大倫火山
Vesvi
跟維斯維火山
do some comparisons
做一些比較
what does he have the same
他有什麼相同
how is he different
他有什麼不同
then we know
那我們就知道說
what will happen to him
他會有什麼樣的結果
So according to this very simple introduction
所以根據這樣的很簡單的介紹
I probably have six of these
我大概就分為六個這個
Let me tell you about this
這個內容來跟大家講
The first, of course, is nothing more than
第一個當然不外乎就是
Let me introduce the relationship between Pompeii and Vesvi
龐貝跟維斯維的關係跟大家介紹
We all know each other well
一起來大家都很熟
Maybe some people are a little blurry
那也許有些人稍微模糊一點
Let us now briefly introduce the space-time background
我們現在把時空背景稍微跟大家介紹一下
let everyone know a little bit
讓大家有一點認識
And the main part is to say
而且主要這一部分是說
when the volcano erupts
火山噴發的時候
Why did it cause the entire city of Pompeii
為什麼會造成龐貝古城的整個
the whole is submerged
整個被淹沒
what kind of disaster it has
它有什麼樣的災害
By the way we introduce it
順便我們把它介紹
Then the second is
然後第二個就是
Taipei and Datong volcanoes
台北跟大同火山群
Just now the vice president also said
剛剛副院長也講說
it's a volcano
它就是一個火火山
In fact, this is what we have done in the past ten years
其實這是我們過去十年來的
Some of our like-minded friends in the academic world
我們這個志同套合的一些學界的朋友
Results from different observations
從不同的觀測做出來的結果
it looks like a volcano
看起來它是個火火山
That's especially my own work on this magma chamber
那特別我自己對於這個岩漿庫的工作
It actually took me a lot of time
其實是花了我蠻多的時間
Sometimes I'm embarrassed to speak in private
有時候私底下不好意思講說
In ancient times, I heard people say
古時候就聽人家講說
Grind one piece in this decade
這個十年磨一件
I have that deep feeling
我就有那種深深的感覺
I spent more than ten years
我超過花了十年的時間
finally put
終於把
Want to Answer Questions Do Some Find Some Answers
想回答的問題做一些找到一些答案
The fourth part is TVO
那第四部分就是說TVO
This aunt volcano is alive with this aunt volcano
這大嬸火山跟這大嬸火山活的
and threatening
而且有威脅性
But it's not such a scary thing
但是也不是那麼可怕的事情
as long as we are ready
只要我們有準備
That preparation is actually based on scientific monitoring
那準備其實就是靠科學的監測
scientific knowledge
科學的知識
In fact, it can provide us with many ways to deal with
其實可以提供我們很多應對的方法
that fifth part is fun
那第五部分是好玩
This is not for fun
這個不是跟大家分享好玩
for me personally
對我個人來講
I studied ninth science
我學了第九科學
And it specializes in the study of earthquakes.
而且是專攻就是地震的研究
When I saw the place name of this volcano
當我看到這個火山的地名
Heartbeat with the Volcano
跟火山心跳
I'm really an official
我真的是嘆為官子
That heartbeat like a volcano
那個像火山的心跳
I believe no one in the world has seen
我相信全世界沒有人看到過
when i first saw
當我第一次看到
I don't think there is such a thing
我覺得怎麼會有這種東西
I will report to you later
那待會跟大家報告
Finally, a summary and discussion
最後就是一個總結跟討論
So I'm just posting this
所以我就發入這個
Explain to everyone one by one
跟大家逐一的說明
Let's talk about Pompeii first
那先講這個龐貝跟
Vivo Hill
跟這個維持維活山
the italian peninsula
就是義大利半島
Rome
羅馬
Then to the south of it is
然後它的南邊就是
next to the ancient city
旁邊的古城
Next to the ancient city is the volcano Vesuvius
古城的旁邊就是有維蘇威的火山
that feeling is
那這種感覺就是
the roman empire was very
羅馬帝國非常
when very strong
非常強大的時候
The economy is very good in all aspects
經濟各方面都是很好
actually
其實
many have
很多有
accomplished or
有成就或者
VIP is simple VIP
VIP很簡單的VIP
It will be next to the ancient city here
它就會在旁邊古城這裡
to buy a villa
去買一個別墅
just come here for vacation
就來這邊度假
why come here for vacation
為什麼要來這邊度假
In fact, the world probably
其實全世界大概
There are such phenomena
都有這樣的現象
Near the volcano are the most
火山旁邊都是最
most beautiful
最漂亮的
like tokyo in japan
像日本的東京
everybody knows
大家都知道
Next to Mount Fuji
旁邊的富士山也是
about 60 kilometers
60公里左右
that's japanese
那是日本人的
spirit or fly to a place where it is not possible
精神或者飛去不可的一個地方
that's actually like
那其實就像
Then he came back to Taipei
然後他回來台北
Taipei
台北
where will this rich man be
這個有錢的人都會在哪裡
You have to support yourself to build some mansions, right?
都要養得去弄一些豪宅對不對
Because there are mountains and water
因為那邊有山有水
just beautiful
就是很漂亮
so like
所以就像
As long as there are volcanoes in the world
全世界只要有火山的地方
basically just pretty
基本上就是非常漂亮
that is
就是
It's a place that makes you feel comfortable
就是讓你覺得很舒服的地方
but
但是
Of course he has his threats
當然他有他的威脅性
2000 years ago
當初2000年前
The science of course is almost zero
這個科學當然是幾乎是零
so they also
所以他們也
didn't expect these things
沒想到這些事情
so right here
所以就在這邊
built this ancient city
建了這個旁邊古城
If you have the opportunity to go now
那你如果現在有機會去
or have the opportunity to
或者有機會去
This is Vizvi
這是維茲威火山
This is the current appearance of the ancient city
這是古城的現在的外貌
After everyone is excavated
大家被挖掘以後
The rest becomes a
剩下的變成是一個
Very
非常
very this
非常這個
one for many people to visit
多人去觀光的一個
a museum
一個博物館
or attractions
或者景點
Then of course the result of this is
那當然這個的結果就是
When Vizvi volcano erupted
維茲威火山噴發的時候
take this
把這個
This is from the movie
這個是電影裡面的
the plot is
情節就是
The entire ancient city of Pangbei will be covered.
把整個旁貝的古城就蓋掉了
Then review these relevant knowledge
那回顧一下這些相關的知識
this
這個
Visvi and Pombe
維斯維跟旁貝古城
In fact, Weisvi is in the ancient city of Pompei to the south of him
其實維斯維在旁貝古城在他的南邊
About 10 kilometers away
大概距離差不多10公里左右
The gray one means that
那灰灰的這個是代表說
volcanic ash
火山灰
When the volcano erupted, the volcanic ash covered the entire area.
火山噴發的時候火山灰蓋著大概這個區域整個都蓋出了
so in
所以在
During the eruption in 2000, the entire ancient city of Pompei was covered with 6 meters of volcanic ash
2000年級噴發的時候整個旁貝古城蓋了6公尺的火山灰
In fact, nothing is gone
其實就什麼都不見了
That
那
The survey at the time said that there were probably
當時的調查說大概有
20,000 people live in Pombe
2萬人居住在旁貝
And what is the emphasis on
而且特別強調的是什麼
in the holiday villa
在假日的別墅中
Everyone is relaxing over there
大家很悠閒的在那邊
on vacation
度假的過程中
It was not until the 16th century when the canal was opened
那直到這個16世紀的時候這個開著這個運河的時候才把
Found an ancient wall but
發現有古墻但是
to this
到了這個
In the 18th century, the king wanted to have these ancient arts
18世紀的時候這個國王為了有這些古代的藝術的
young cause
幼因
So he spent a lot of money to put this street in Pompey
所以他就花了很多錢把這個龐佩的街道啊
A lot of antiquities, just dig it out
很多古物啊什麼就把它挖掘出來
That's why people know
所以才 人們才知道說
Oh, this used to be a very big city
喔 這裡曾經是一個非常這個有規模的城市
Although only twenty thousand
雖然只有兩萬
But you can imagine 20,000 people two thousand years ago
但是你可以想像兩千年前的兩萬
It's a very lively city
那是非常熱鬧的一個城市的
Then they dug this
那他們的挖出來這個
You see, the streets are very well planned
你看這街道都是非常有規劃的
worthy of work
值得起班式的
and especially this
然後特別這個
This one has a giant merchant's house above it
這個有一個巨商的房子上面
It will say on the ground, this money
地上會寫著喔 這個錢啊
This welcome money welcomes you
這個歡迎錢喔 歡迎你喔
It means they are extravagant
就是代表他們很奢侈
In fact, go to Google to find this literature theory
其實這個文獻理論去google找一下
There are many criticisms
有很多很多的批判喔
It was the luxury of the life of the Romans at that time
就是當時 當時羅馬人他們的生活的奢侈
Or a lot of negative words are in it
或者很多很多負面的言詞都在裡面喔
Then of course the last
那當然最後就是
They don't know the money is waiting for you
他們也不知道這個錢等著你
But the volcano is there too
但是火山也有就在那邊
In fact, two sides of the same body
其實一體兩面
Then why did this happen in the end?
那最後為什麼會造成這樣
This is what we want to convey to you
這也是我們想跟大家傳達
What kind of threat does the volcano pose to me?
就是火山對我什麼樣的威脅
Then this is the original
那這個是當初的這些
These residents were instantly overwhelmed by high temperature
這些居民瞬間被高溫的
When pyroclastic volcanoes are buried
火山碎屑火山也會埋住的時候
In fact, your bone and flesh tissue is gone in an instant.
其實你的骨肉組織就瞬間就不見了
But your body becomes hollow
但是你那個趨體就變成空洞
This is because they poured plaster into it
這個是他們是灌石膏進去
look like people at that time
把當時人的模樣
helped it out
把它互援出來的
why is that so
那為什麼會這樣
In fact, I want to introduce to you
其實就是要跟大家介紹就是說
this pyroclastic
這個火山碎屑
this is real
這是真實拍的
Because Pompeii in the 2000s
因為2000年代的龐貝古城
There is no way to testify
已經沒辦法考據了
But volcanic activity
但是火山的活動
In fact, there will always be
其實是一直都會有的
crumbs
就是所謂的碎屑
What does this photo look like?
看起來這個照片就超像什麼
Super like this sand leopard
超像這個沙塵豹
Anyway, it's just a cloud of ashes.
反正就是一團的灰那樣
so you can't see what you're wearing
讓你看不出穿的
But this is totally different from the Dust Leopard
但是這跟沙塵豹是完全不一樣的
Dust Leopard, look at this speed is very fast
沙塵豹你看這個速度非常快
100 kilometers per hour 200 kilometers per hour
每小時100公里 200公里的速度
Then this is very hot
然後這個是非常高溫
hundreds of degrees of high temperature
數百度的高溫
It means you can't escape
意思是說你也逃不掉
if you are touched by it
那你被它碰到的話
In fact, probably like the inhabitants of Pompeii
其實大概就跟龐貝古城的居民
almost identical
幾乎是一模一樣的
so you see this
所以你看到這個
These are some village houses on the hillside
山坡上面這些有些村莊房子
Actually you can imagine this
其實你可以想像這個一下來
In fact, there will be nothing left
其實什麼都不會留著
would have exactly the same result as Pompeii.
就會跟龐貝古城一模一樣的結果
then this is all real
那這個是都是真實的
This is a Filipino brand
這是菲律賓品牌
when my volcano erupts
我火山噴發的時候
you can see
你可以看到
There's one in the lower left corner, a little bit of a truck
左下角有一個,有一點卡車
see this stream
看到這個碎穴流
certainly
當然
Run if you can run, jump into a car if you can
能跑就跑,能跳上車就跳上車
run fast
趕快加速的跑
But like I just said, can these people escape?
但是就像我剛剛講的,這些人跑得掉嗎?
Basically, you can't run away, because the speed of this broken hole is faster than the car on Gao Ai Nurse Highway
基本上是跑不掉,因為這碎穴流速度比高愛護士公路的車子還快
What's more, this is a path in the field
何況這個是田間的小路
That
那
Also in the same year, this silvery volcano in Japan
同樣在同一年,日本的這個銀炫火山
You can google this, you can see this video
這個你可以去google一下,你可以看到這個影片
He is here, the car is here, and when he sees the broken hole, run quickly
他就人在這邊,車子在這邊,看到碎穴流,趕快跑
Then the broken hole flow keeps coming and going, and then
然後這個碎穴流就一直過來過來過來,然後就
The screen goes black, and then why do I see
螢幕就黑掉,然後為什麼看到
Later, people took this camera and put it
後來人家把這個camera,把它
Take it out, since that record is still there
拿出來,既然那個紀錄還在
he played it back
他把它playback
Then restore it to the process at that time
然後就把它還原當時的過程
So the cavitation flow is actually for volcanic disasters, it is
所以碎穴流其實對於火山災害裡面,它是
first place
第一名的
It's hard to guard against, and you probably won't be able to run away when you see it
這是防不勝防,而且你看到它大概跑不掉
it's very very scary
這是非常非常可怕的
Then why are there crumbs? There is a very simple cartoon explanation diagram for this
那為什麼會有碎屑有,這個有一個很簡單的卡通解釋圖
Because when the magma keeps coming up from the crater
因為岩漿從火山口一直上來的時候
That's a thousand-degree high-temperature thing
那是上千度的高溫的東西
After coming straight up, it's starting to cool down a bit after this side
垂直上來之後,到這邊以後它開始有點要冷卻
But still a few hundred degrees left
可是還是幾百度剩
but it starts off kind of turning into something solid
但是它開始就會有點變成固體的東西
It just turns into stone energy, and it will feel a little cooling down slowly
就是變成石頭能量,慢慢就會有點冷卻的感覺
But when it keeps piling up
但是它一直往上堆高的時候
Because of gravity, it will eventually collapse
因為重力的關係,它最後會崩塌
so when it accumulates a lot
所以當它累積很多很多的時候
When it collapsed in an instant, a debris flow was generated
一瞬間崩塌的時候就產生了碎屑流
Underneath are small stones or these large and small stones
底下是小石頭或者這些大大小的石頭
There's volcanic ash on it, and it's all down
上面就是火山灰,它整個就下來
So this is the one that threatens the most
所以這個是威脅人最多的一種
And what I just said is because of the high temperature
然後剛剛講的就是因為是高溫
Look at this, as soon as you get down, the whole house burns down
你看這個,只要下來瞬間整個房子怎麼都燃燒掉了
which one is the most
那一個最
The most modern, and the best example of this, is the Ginsen Volcano in Japan
最現代的,而且最好的例子就是日本的銀仙火山
This is the eruption of this Yinxian volcano
這是這個銀仙火山的噴發
Then this is Shimabara Temple, just at the foot of the mountain
那這個就是島原寺,就在山腳下
And then this tax leak comes from this hilltop
然後這個稅泄流就從這個山頂
Just go down the whole valley
就整個沿著這個山谷就下來
So what happened?
那發生什麼事情呢?
an arrow like this
就是類似這樣的箭頭
This is a tax leak, just go down this valley
這個是稅泄流就沿著這個谷地就下來
The one that digs low is like a river
那這個比較低挖的,它就好像河流
So the main tax stones
這樣就主要的這些稅石頭啊
that would go along these low valleys
那就會沿著這個低的這些谷地走
but here it takes a turn
但是在這裡它有個轉彎
turn these stones
轉彎這些石頭
it's heavier, it goes this way
它比較重,它就沿著這邊走
But what does this one arrow represent?
但是這一個箭頭代表什麼?
It's just ash, a lighter substance
它就是灰,比較輕的物質
it has no friction against the ground
它沒有碰到地的摩擦力
It's coming straight from here, right here
它直接就從這裡,就直接衝過來
Then rush over here is the village
那衝過來這裡就是村莊
There is a primary school in the village
村莊這裡有一個小學
Let's see what's going on in this elementary school
我們看這個小學到底發生什麼事情
this is this
這個是這個
This crumb came from here
這個碎屑有從這邊過來
so we are
所以我們是
crumbs have from this
碎屑有從這個
Come over from the back of the classroom
教室的背面過來
Of course you can see the glass
當然你可以看到這些玻璃
all
全部都
by that
就被那個
those with crumbs
碎屑有的那些
break it apart
揮把它整裂的
Whole
整碎的
but if you look
但是你如果看
the other side
另外那一邊
what can you see
你可以看到什麼
this is
這個是
Lee doors and windows
李門窗
You can imagine how hot that temperature is
你可以想像那個溫度有大多高
That's volcanic ash
那個就是火山灰
that hundreds of degrees of temperature
那個幾百度的溫度
come in an instant
瞬間過來
Li Menchuang
就把李門窗
That's the same temperature
那個那一相當的溫度
deformed throughout
整個都變形
so you imagine saying this thing
所以你想像說這個東西
very hot stuff
很高溫的東西
Li doors and windows are deformed
李門窗都變形了
you can imagine people
你可以想像人
or all these houses
或者所有這些房子
General traditional wooden or house
一般的傳統的木或房子
It burns in an instant
一下子瞬間就燃燒掉了
That's actually
那其實
Silver Circle volcano on top of history
銀圈火山在歷史上面
In fact, for Japan
其實對日本來講
very, very many hard lessons
非常非常多是慘痛的教訓
this 1792
這個1792年
Fifteen thousand deaths from this
這造成的一萬五千人死亡
why hundreds of years ago
幾百年前的為什麼呢
This is actually a worthwhile
這其實是一個值得我們
One of these natural disasters around the world
這個全世界的這些自然災害的一個
This model of understanding
這個認識的範本
then how could this be
那這怎麼會是呢
That's when the volcano erupted
就是已經火山噴發的時候
Just like the eruption of Xiahaoyi volcano just now
就像剛剛這個夏浩益火山噴發
cause an earthquake of about seven
就引發一個大概七左右的地震
Then this earthquake of course the damage of the earthquake
然後這地震當然地震的破壞
we can imagine
我們可以想而知
even more frightening
更可怕的是
He put the other side of this silver announcement
他把這個銀宣的另外這邊
there was a mountain
本來有個山頭
shake it all down
整個把它震滑了
He just slides into the sea
他就整個滑到這個海裡面去
If it slips into the sea, it will generate a tsunami
滑到海裡了就產生海嘯
So this typical
所以這典型的
A compound disaster is a volcano, an earthquake, three eruptions and a tsunami
複合式災害就是火山地震三噴海嘯
15,000 people
真正一萬五千人
probably more than ten thousand people
可能超過一萬人
They all died from the impact of this tsunami
都是死在這個海嘯的衝擊
Then this is Yinxuan Volcano in Kyushu
那這個就是九州的銀宣火山
he is here
他就在這兒
So you see this to this landslide to
所以你看這個到這個山崩到
Ocean
海
In fact, all the residents of the surrounding seaside villages in the Inner Sea suffered disaster.
其實整個內海的周遭的海邊的村莊居民全部遭殃
That's why there are so many casualties
所以才會造成這麼多的傷亡
So the Fowles disaster is now more familiar to everyone.
所以富爾斯災害現在已經大家比較熟悉
Like Japan's Three World Wars and One Earthquake
像日本的三戰一地震
We all know about earthquakes, tsunamis, river disasters
大家都知道地震、海嘯、河災
River disasters may actually be more beautiful and perfect than earthquakes and tsunamis
河災其實可能是比地震海嘯更美完美了
So that is to say, from the very beginning of this event
所以就是說從這個一開始的這個事件
In fact, the most serious thing is the last one
引發到最後其實最嚴重是最後頭的
So the Fuers disaster is actually relevant to what we are talking about now.
所以這個富爾斯災害其實對於我們現在在講
This disaster prevention is very important
這個防災是很重要的
if i know soon what's going on with this
我如果很快能知道這個發生什麼事情
I have time to avoid subsequent actions
我就有時間去避免後續的一些動作
or some disaster
或者一些災害
Therefore, Fuers disaster is a very important concept for disaster prevention in the world.
所以富爾斯災害是全世界對於防災的一個很重要的概念
Well, let's talk about this same thing, which of course hasn't happened yet.
好 那講這個同樣的這當然還沒有發生
This is what many American advanced European scientists worry about
這是很多美國先進歐洲的科學家擔心的
This is Africa This is North America South America
這是非洲 這是北美 南美
On the west coast of Africa there is a volcanic island
在非洲的西岸這裡有一個火山島
volcanic islands likewise they serve as
火山島同樣的它們擔任
When the volcano erupts, the volcanic island will collapse
火山噴發的時候火山島會垮
or these very steep terrain
或者這些很陡峭的地形
As long as it collapses, there will be a tsunami
只要奔塌的話就會產生海嘯
Then the scientist is free to do some simulations
那這科學家沒事做一些模擬
but scary
但是怪可怕的
look at these numbers
你看這些數字
it's 132 meters
這是132公尺
Which city or 132 us if
哪個城市或是132我們如果
In Shancheng Princess, we may all soak in the sea here
在山城公主我們在這邊可能都泡到海裡面去
inside sea water
海水裡面
That
那
Although in the west of Africa
雖然在非洲的西邊
But New York and Boston in the United States
但是美國的紐約波士頓
or many cities on the east coast
或者東岸的很多城市
As long as this tsunami comes
這個海嘯只要過來的話
This is really out of hand
這個其實真的不可收拾
It is a great threat to mankind and the United States
對人類對美國都是很大的威脅
Will this be a serious problem?
那這個會不會發生極力的問題
Now none of us can tell
現在我們誰就說不上
but what day is the real volcanic activity
但是哪一天真的火山活動
become a disaster caused by a tsunami
變成海嘯造成的災害
is a question worth thinking about
是值得我們去思考的問題
Although every week in Africa seems to have nothing to do with us
雖然在非洲每週好像跟我們沒關係
I especially take the opportunity to point out
我特別藉著機會指出來
That is to say, everyone knows about Guishan Island.
就是說這個大家都知道貴山島
I didn't talk about Guishan Island today
貴山島我今天沒有談
But Guishan Island is outside the Big Butt Volcano
但是貴山島是大臀火山以外的
volcanically active volcanic island in taiwan
台灣的火山活動火山島
If you have been to Guishan Island
那貴山島如果去過的話
You can see that these terrains are very steep
你就看到這些地形就非常陡峭
If a volcanic event takes this piece
如果一個火山活動把這一塊
array it like this
把它陣列了像這種
This is of course a simulation
這當然是個模擬
It also creates waves or tsunamis
同樣也造成海浪或者叫海嘯
In particular, our Yilan Plain is actually very flat, right?
特別我們的宜蘭平原其實非常的平對不對
Waves of five meters may occur on the Yilan Plain
宜蘭平原可能五公尺的海浪
is the tsunami
就是海嘯
Maybe the beach is the same
可能海邊的就照樣
if ten meters
如果十公尺
There is no need for a third of Yilan to be soaked in water
沒必要三分之一個宜蘭會泡在水裡
Well, of course we don't want this to happen.
那這個我們當然不希望發生
But what happens in nature is not whether we rest or not
可是大自然的事情不是我們息不希望
that we have to be prepared
就是我們要有準備
Can't wait until we wish it didn't happen
不能等到我們希望它不要發生就好了
back to this volcanic disaster
回到這個火山災
The world trends I just told you about are the scariest.
剛剛跟大家講的這些世界流是最可怕的
That Long Yanliu is like this Xia Fuyi
那龍煙流像這個夏浮誼這種
dragon smoke is hot but it's not scary
龍煙流是很高溫但是它不可怕
there's a little bit of what's actually it's slow
有一點什麼其實它很慢
you see it you run probably past it
你看到它你跑大概跑過它
Therefore, the disaster of Longyanliu is actually relatively limited.
所以龍煙流的災害其實相對是很有限的
The other thing is that we mentioned the earthquake just now.
那另外就是我們剛剛講地震有提過了
Let's talk about the volcanic glow and mudflow
我們再講這個火山輝跟泥流
Special Volcano Hui we just talked about
特別火山輝我們剛剛講的
Don't talk about the flow of the world, dragons and smoke are all at close range
不講世界流龍煙流都是近距離的
it's only dangerous if you touch it
你碰到它才會危險
But Volcano is not
但是火山輝就不是
it can go far
它可以好遠好遠的
cause you a lot of trouble
就造成你很大的困擾
This was also last month
這是也是上個月
Yindao volcano erupts again
陰島火山又噴發的
Luer Island next to it is Yin Island
旁邊的路兒島就是陰島
This is Lugoshima City
這邊就是路兒島市
The city of Luer Island has probably remained the same, with about 500,000 people.
路兒島市大概沒變差不多50萬人吧
small cities
左右不大不小的城市
this volcanic glow
這個火山輝
The sound instructor is very active
音導師超活躍的
I'm going to the audio guide
我去音導
5 to 10 times
5到10次吧
i won't remember
我會不記得
about twice
大概兩次
There will be a volcanic glow once
就有一次會碰到火山輝
I have a high memory
就記憶蠻高的
I often go to see the volcanic glow
常常去就看到火山輝
It's coming up like a chimney
就跟煙囪一樣就上來了
What about the result?
那結果呢
this lure tutor is like this
這個路爾導師就像這樣
This is either going to sea or volcanic glow
這個不是下海就是火山輝的關係
So Mr. Lure is very used to
所以路爾導師已經非常習慣
This Volcanic Fai follows them
這個火山輝跟他們
live together
一起這個生活
That
那
Mount Aso two years ago
兩年前的阿蘇火山
Just the whole surrounding city
就整個旁邊城市的這些
The car is all covered
車子全部被覆蓋住
This of course just causes you
這當然只是會造成你
life is very inconvenient
生活很不方便
It will not cause your life and property
還不會造成你的生命財產的
big threat
很大的威脅
That's a small volcanic eruption
那這是小的火山噴發
But the volcano had a big eruption
但是火山有大的噴發
eruptions smaller than
比小的噴發
Like this one in the 900 million year old Philippines
像9億年的菲律賓的這個
Pinglaotupu erupts here
平老土土埔在這邊噴發
This is where Manila is located
這是馬尼拉的位置
Usually Tupu is in
平常土埔就在
This volcano has actually been in the past ten or twenty years
這個火山其實已經在過去一二十年來
Already a relatively large volcano
已經算比較大的火山
what effect it has
那它造成的影響
because this volcano is very lucky
因為不過這個火山非常幸運
why lucky
為什麼幸運
Because the United States has a so-called air base in the Philippines
因為美國在菲律賓有所謂的空軍基地
That's Clark Air Force Base.
就是克拉克空軍基地這個
They were two weeks before the eruption
他們在火山噴發的前兩個禮拜
Because the USGS in the United States helped with the investigation
因為美國的USGS幫忙做調查
Because of the problem with their F-16 fighter jets
因為關係著他們的F-16戰鬥機的問題
So they found out they couldn't do it.
所以他們調查結果說不行了
This volcano should erupt within ten days
這個火山十天以內應該會噴發
All the F-16s at Clark AFB have flown away
所有克拉克空軍基地的F-16全部都飛走了
only this one left
只剩下這一座
This is a broken plane
這個是已經壞掉的飛機
it can't run so keep it
它跑不了 所以就留著
So a lot of volcanoes were built
所以就蓋了很多的火山會
This is a very successful
這個是一個非常成功的
Successful examples of volcano monitoring
火山監測的成功的例子
Of course, the United States and the Philippines
那當然是美國跟菲律賓
result of cooperation
合作的結果
then look at this
那你看這個
Although this has these volcanic ash at close range
這個雖然在近距離有這些火山灰
But this volcanic ash is not only
可是這個火山灰不是只有
Will it affect the vicinity?
在附近會影響呢
you see this is
你看這個是
this before the eruption
噴發前的這個
tens of kilometers of this
幾十公里的這個
These ash
平六成的這些灰
june eruption
六月一噴發
all turn red
整個都變紅色
That volcanic ash drifts to
那個火山灰就飄到
very very high peak go
非常非常高的高峰去
then you see this is
然後你看這是
august to december
八月到了十二月
slowly recovered
才慢慢的又恢復到
restore to original
恢復到原始
So about half a year
所以大概有半年左右的時間
The whole of this volcanic ash is in
整個這個火山灰就在
high up on earth
在地球的這個高空
With the wind
飄
Although this is
那這個雖然是
Larger volcanoes this year
今年比較大的火山
But if you follow history
但是你如果跟歷史
It is the kind of big volcanic eruption in the historical era
就是歷史年代那種大的火山噴發
can take the whole earth
可以把整個地球的
of
的
the whole atmosphere is covered
整個大氣都蓋住
do not come in
不進來
creatures of the earth
地球的生物
or
或者
will even become extinct
甚至會滅絕
This is history
這是歷史上面有
That's what the historical evidence says
就是歷史上面的證據有說
extinction of some creatures
一些生物的滅絕
In fact, it may be related to the volcano
其實有可能跟火山
Large volcanic eruptions are closely related
大的火山噴發有很密集的關係
well that
好 那
In 2011 this Icelandic volcano
2011年這個冰島火山
Maybe everyone has the impression
可以可能大家都有印象
So a volcano erupts
所以火山一噴
The entire volcano will float to the continent of Europe
整個火山會就飄到歐洲的大陸
All flights across continental Europe are grounded
整個歐洲的大陸的航班全部都停板
The whole traveler
那整個這個旅客啊
or the economy
或者經濟啊什麼
They assess a whole bunch of losses
他們就評估一大堆的損失
Then this is a bigger volcano
那這個是大一點的火山
In fact, it's not just the effect of close range.
其實不是只有近距離的影響
In fact, all human beings will be affected
其實全人類都會受到影響
Let's see how much it erupts
那看它噴發的量有多大
That
那
Probably the largest volcano is nothing more than this one
大概講大的火山不外乎這一個
this is america
這個是美國
above the address they have three different colors
在地址上面他們有三次不同的色彩
That's 2.2 million years
就是220萬年
1.32 million years
132萬年
640,000 years
64萬年
Area covered by three eruptions of different ages
三次不同年代火山噴發的覆蓋的區域
Geologist doing occupational survey
地質學家做職業調查
outlined
勾勒出來的
So there's a super nutrition store under Yellowstone Park
所以在黃石公園底下有個超級的營養庫
This also has a movie in production
這個也有電影在產生
It's also very sensational
也是非常的這個聳動
or very scary
或非常可怕
So the United States is actually very important to this Yellowstone Park.
所以美國對於這個黃石公園其實是
is very, very serious to treat
是非常非常的認真的去對待
Why
為什麼
Of course you divide 2.2 by 13
當然你把2.2除13
About once every 700,000 years
大概就是70萬年就來一次
So last time it was 640,000
所以上一次是64萬
seems to be coming soon
好像快要到了
If round by cycle
如果用周期來輪
If it is true, it represents their age
如果是真的話代表他們在第幾年代的時候
Seems like it's about to erupt
好像第幾時間的時候已經快要噴發了
This is the result of a supervolcano
這個是超級火山的結果
Volcanic ash certainly has a big impact
火山灰當然就影響很大
Let's go back to this lahar
我們回到這個火山泥流
That's the lahar flow in Colombia, Central America.
就是哥倫比亞,中美洲的火山泥流
What is a volcanic mudflow? We have it in Taiwan
什麼叫火山泥流?我們台灣有
Everyone knows this landslide
這個土石流,大家都知道
It's just water, mud, or he just flows down
就是水、泥、或者他就流下來
It's even scarier at the volcano
那在火山更可怕
volcanic ash is lighter
火山灰是更輕
so it is easier to flow
所以它是更容易流動
And the ash is very thick in the volcanic area
而且火山灰在火山地區又很厚
So all at once the whole mudslide comes over
所以只要一下子就整個泥流就過來
that's especially this
那特別這個
This is in the mountains of Central America
這個是在中美洲這些高山
Usually like Yushan
平常就像玉山
or higher these mountains
或者更高的這些山
it is covered with snow
它上面都蓋著下雪
But once the volcano came up,
但是火山一上來以後
Is a high temperature with ice, snow, dragon
就是一個高溫跟冰、雪、龍
When you touch some of that snow, it will melt
碰到一些那個雪就融
produce a lot of water
就產生大量的水
Then the water brings down the ash
然後水就把火山灰帶下來
The whole shock
整個這種衝擊其實
There are tens of thousands of people
動不動就是幾萬人
This is because it was far away from us in China and the United States.
這個因為在中美時候離我們很遠
But in fact, the transmission of information
但是其實現在資訊的傳達
if you look carefully
你如果仔細去看
this is
這種就是
There will be such a big disaster in five or ten years
五年十年就有這種大的災難
will run out
會跑出來
that mud flow is like this
那泥流就像這樣子
the whole of this
整個這個
Landslides in the South before Typhoon August 8
八八風災前南部的土石流
In fact, after the main disaster of these rivers
其實就把這些河道主災以後
Then the water goes into the village
然後水就到村莊裡面去
flooding
泛濫成災
This is the moment when the volcano erupts
這個是火山奔發瞬間
Just so we said volcanic ash lahars
就剛好我們就說火山灰火山泥流
volcanic ash
火山灰溶溶溶
Water leaks, this is an instant disaster
水泄流這是瞬間的災害
But this mudslide
但這隻泥流
this is endless
這是沒完沒了
Why
為什麼
just a typhoon
只要一個颱風
water comes
水來
just bring a mudslide
就帶一個泥流
especially the philippines
特別是菲律賓
Philippines at every turn
菲律賓動不動
as long as a typhoon comes
只要一個颱風來
Of course we are in Taiwan
我們台灣當然
are often threatened by typhoons
也常常受到颱風很大的威脅
But like the brand is the one next to me
可是像品牌就是我旁邊那個
that is
那個就是
The volcanic ash is carried all the time
火山灰就一直帶一直帶把
the river
河道
Then the whole flood was changed to a lot of villages
然後就洪水就整個換到到很多的村莊群
that may be thirty years
那可能三十年
That volcano will not be taken away
那個火山會還帶不走
Then keep repeating these
那一直就一直repeat這些
menacing thing
威脅性的東西
well that
好 那
Give a general introduction to Vesvi and Pompeii or volcanoes
把維斯維跟龐貝或者火山大概做一個介紹
We will go directly back to our Taipei and Mainland China
我們就直接回到我們台北跟大陸山
Of course this is imaginary
那這當然是想像的
This is our 101 Dalun Volcano in Taipei Basin
這個是我們的101台北盆地大倫火山
What if the Great Looming erupted?
大倫火山如果噴發 如果
These dragonfly flows, crater flows, or lahars
這些龍蝇流 碎穴流或者火山泥流
Anyway, Xianjian Huohuo may all go to the Taipei Basin
反正仙劍火火可能都到台北盆地
Then if these dragon flies block the entrance of Guandu
那如果這些龍蝇流把關渡這個口堵住了
Danshui and Keelung can't get out
那淡水和基隆出不去
Will there be this legendary Kangxi Taipei Lake?
是不是會有這個傳說的康熙台北湖
won't run out
也不會跑出來
So as long as it happens there is a possibility
所以只要發生就有這個可能性
The distance is actually
那這個距離其實
I really hope to connect 101 with Qixing Mountain
我很希望把101跟七星山
In fact, we think the most likely to live
其實我們認為最有可能活
active area
活動的區域
Well, it's actually less than 15 kilometers
那其實它是小於15公里
is a very very short distance
是非常非常短的距離
Very short straight line distance
直線距離非常短
You can imagine the volcano bit coming up
你可以想像火山位一上來
The whole of Taipei probably
整個台北大概可能
with the guide for
跟那個引導的對於
The city next to it has almost the same impact
那個旁邊的城市影響差不多
Then we also do a little bit of simulation
那我們也做一點點模擬
This is assuming that there is a volcanic eruption in Qixing Mountain
這是假設七星山有火山噴發
What will happen to Longweiliu
龍威流會怎樣
This is the simulated location
這是模擬的位置
Then you give me a little closer look
那你給我稍微靠近一點看
The different colors are its thickness
不同的色彩就是它的厚度
or its area of influence
或者它的影響範圍
Then don't look carefully at this
那這個大家不要仔細看
because you'll see
因為你會看說
where is my home
我家在哪裡
then i will
那我就
In fact, I have always
其實這一張圖我一直
I made it about four or five years ago
我大概四五年前我就做出來
I have never dared to show off
我都一直不太敢秀
Until recently because volcanoes in the sea have been
直到最近因為火山在海已經是
Is it legislation?
就是立法了嘛
When the government is going to face
那政府要去面對的時候
so
所以
This is for reference only
這個僅共參考
that's for
那是對於
If it's Mount Suzui, it's underground, it's Jinshan
那如果是黃嘴山,這是底下,這是金山
Just to the north, we know that Jinshan is very productive.
就是往北邊,金山我們知道很能產啊
In fact, many people are very concerned
其實也很多人很關心啊
Will it have an impact on very productive
會不會對很能產的影響
I don't comment on this
這個我都不comment
just do a little mock work
只是做一點點模擬的工作
that of course affects the range
那當然會影響範圍
It all depends on the amount it erupts, right?
完全看它噴發的量嘛對不對
It erupts a little bit, of course it has a very small area of effect
噴發的有一點點它當然影響範圍很小
If the amount of eruption is large
如果噴發的量很大
It certainly has a large reach
它當然影響範圍很大
that eruption is small
那噴發大很小
now we don't know
現在我們不知道
but i'll tell you later
但是我待會跟你講說
if it
如果它
erupting next month
下個月要噴發
I have a very high chance
我大概有很高很高的機率
will tell everyone
會跟大家講說
Will the eruption be big or small
會噴發是大還是小
This is an opinion with some scientific estimates
這是有科學的一些估算的意見
well, this volcanic ash
好,這個火山灰
It is also what people often talk about
也是大家常常會談的
This is the public health teacher of CUHK
這個是中大網公衛老師
help with some simulations
幫忙做的一些模擬
In fact, he did it 365 days a year
其實他做了一年365天
According to different seasons, different directions
根據不同的季節,不同的方向
when the volcano comes up
火山上來的時候
how should it float
應該會怎麼飄
Then of course we have 365 days of data
那這個當然我們有365天的Data
we are all running
我們都在RUN
I'm here only spring and autumn
我這裡只是春天跟秋天
Of course spring, summer, autumn and winter are different
春夏秋冬當然不一樣
Every day actually has something to do with the direction of the wind
那每一天其實跟風向有關係
That was six years ago
那這個是在六年前
When our TVO was established
我們這個TVO成立的時候
we just want to say
我們就想說
If the volcano erupts that day
那一天如果火山噴發
How should volcanic ash spread?
火山灰應該怎麼擴散
Just go to Japan to this
就是往日本往這個
Spread in this direction of Hainan Island
海南島這個方向擴散
This is an impression
這是一個印象圖
Just tell these phenomena
就是就告訴這些現象而已
Okay, we talked for a long time
好那談了半天
Actually that's what I've been saying
其實這都是我一直講說
if if if the volcano erupts
如果如果如果火山噴發
if a volcano erupts
如果火山噴發
but the real problem is
但是真的問題就是
Will continental volcanoes erupt?
大陸火山到底會不會噴發
then this is back to us
那這就是回到我們
serious scientific question
很嚴肅的科學問題
And we have been for about ten years
而且是我們大概十幾年來
A group of people trying to find the answer
一群人去努力去找答案的
before finding the answer
那在還沒有找答案之前
when i was a student
我當學生的時候
words read by people in ninth science
在第九科學的人念過的話
So I can know that this is our terrain group in Taipei
所以我可以知道說這是我們台北的地形組
The red area is the fire dust rock
紅色的區域就是火塵岩
Huochen rock is the dragon rock that represents the eruption of the volcano on the surface.
火塵岩就是代表曾經火山噴發的龍岩在地表
igneous rock body
就是火塵岩體
So this is probably like this
所以這個大概是這樣
Because in Taiwan we don't have
因為在台灣我們沒有
There is no record of volcanic eruptions in history
歷史上沒有說火山噴發的紀錄
So most people want to say a volcanic eruption
所以大部分人想說火山噴發
Taiwan dare not do our things
台灣不敢我們的事情
Taipei will never
台北永遠都沒有
But according to geologists to do some dating of these red stones in this area
但是根據地質學家把這些紅色的這個區域的石頭做一些定年
The so-called dating is to find out the age of its eruption
所謂定年就是找出它噴發的年紀
Was it 10,000 years ago, 100,000 years ago, or 1,000,000 years ago?
是一萬年前還是十萬年前還是百萬年前噴
They can do it based on that parity year
他們可以根據那個同位數定年去做
Do the comparison and get the result
做比對然後就得到結果
This is an old picture from the 1980s
這個就是大概1980年代的一張老的圖
That could have had a little eruption about a million years ago
那可以大概一百多萬年前有少許的噴發
At the time of 800,000 years, the
到了八十萬年的時候開始就
Volcanoes began to emerge from Dalin Volcano
大臨火山就開始有火山出來的
then four hundred thousand years more
然後四十萬年更多
Then came this hundred thousand years
然後到了這個十萬年
I feel like it stopped
我覺得是好像停止的
Therefore, because the data are provided for 100,000 years
所以因為資料的提供到十萬年
There is no data for 0.1 million years
零點一個百萬年就沒有資料了
So there is no eruption in history
所以歷史上也沒有噴發
This address home tells us that 100,000 years
這個地址家告訴我們說十萬年
seems to be gone
好像就沒有了
So for a long, long time in the past
所以在過去很長很長的時間
It's been a long time, everyone, the mainland is very common
大家久了大陸很常
Continental Volcanoes or Yangmingshan National Park
大陸火山或陽明山國家公園
just to play
就是去玩的
it's not threatening to us
它對我們沒有什麼威脅性
But about ten years of work
但是大概十幾年來的工作
If we go to mainland volcanoes to see
我們如果去大陸火山看到
This is a surface fumarole hot spring, right?
這是地表噴氣孔溫泉對不對
This is a typical volcanic area
這是滿典型的火山的區域
Especially this geochemical analysis
特別這個地球化學的分析
This is the work done by professors from Taiwan and Taiwan.
這是以前台大兩岸來教授做的工作
He is still equal to the pioneer
他還是等於先驅
He did some of these chemical analyzes of the fumaroles
他做了一些噴氣孔的這些化學的分析
just tell us
告訴我們就說
That thing is not a feature of the surface
那個東西不是地表的特徵
but what
而是什麼
If the earth is not deep, the earth is slow
深不地球來的就是地慢
That's Teacher Yang Cannan
那也是楊燦楠老師
Di Xiaohua learns from the perspective of the flower, it looks like it is alive
滴小花學 花學的角度看起來它是活的
But no one does physics
可是物理的卻沒有人去做
so he advised me to do it
所以他勸我去做
At that time, I just came back from a year-long visit to Japan
那時候我剛好去日本這個訪問一年回來
Saw a lot of volcanoes in Japan
在日本看了很多火山
I just jump in and do it
我就心難就跳進去做
Then I jumped in and now I can't come back
然後一跳進去到現在就回不來了
more and more miracles
就越做越奇蹟
Then anyway, I will cast the Earthquake King
那anyway我就佈了地震王
so i watched a lot
所以我就看了很多的
There are many, many earthquakes in Dalian Mountain
在大連山就好多好多的地震
Then in these earthquakes
然後在這些地震裡面
What particularly attracts me is
特別讓我吸引的就是
There are quite a few volcanic earthquakes to see
有相當的火山地震看得到
The traditional ones are general fault earthquakes and volcanic earthquakes
傳統的就是一般斷層的地震跟火山地震
Its shape and its physical properties are completely different
它的形貌 它的物理特性是完全不一樣的
He has someone to introduce a few
他有一個人介紹幾個
Then, like this air-made radar, you can see the crater burst
然後像這個空造雷達就看到火山口暴裂口
it's all new
這都是很新的
the rep said it wasn't weathered
代表說它沒有被風化掉
didn't get overshadowed by the 10th
沒有被第十年代把它掩蓋掉
mean it's new
意思說它是新的
Then the level car two is Japan one
然後水準車兩是日本一個
A queen uncle of mine used to sit with me
以前我的一個伯後跟我一起坐了
There may be rises and falls
一可會有台升下降
It means he seems to be moving
代表他好像有在動
rather than stable
而不是很穩定的
Then this date is special
然後這個定年特別
last most important
最後一項最重要
this was before
這是以前
Deputy Director Chen Zonghua
我們所理的陳宗華副所長
He took him to Russia
他帶他找了俄羅斯
found a german
找了德國人
I found it because Russia is also full of volcanoes.
找了因為俄羅斯也滿多火山的
Then comes the year of the Volcano Society
然後就來火山會的定年
Because we don't have the
因為我們沒有這方面的
very good expert
很好的專家
So I invite these foreign scholars to help
所以就請這些外國的學者來幫忙
he decided probably
他定出來大概
five thousand to six thousand years
五千年到六千年
Anyway, he made a mistake.
反正他有誤差就是了
But whether it's five thousand or six thousand
但是不管是五千或六千
This means a lot
這個就很高的含義
What does that mean
什麼意思呢
In the Republic of China
在民國
In 1999
99年的時候
We will hold a meeting of experts and scholars at the Geological Survey Institute
我們就在地質調查所開一個專家學者的會議
Then we put Chancellor Volcano
然後我們就把大臣火山
discussed for a long time
討論了很久
Although there are very
雖然中間有極有
strong dispute
很強的爭執
Some people say Yes and No
有人說Yes也跟No
Some people say that ordinary volcanoes
有人就說一般的火火山
Volcanoes are all over the world
火火山就是在全世界
extinct or active volcano
死火山或活火山
Natalon Volcano
那大倫火山
The result of our final discussion is that
我們最後討論的結果就是
dormant volcano
休眠的火火山
What is a dormant volcano
什麼叫休眠火火山
it is a volcano
它是火火山
but it's sleeping now
可是它現在在睡覺
It may not wake up one day
它哪一天沒必會醒過來
Then this living Huohuo Songshan
那這個現生的火火松山
What is the name of the volcano?
火火山叫什麼
Like Xia Haoyi
像夏浩蟻啊
You can go to see that magma anytime
你隨時去看那個岩漿
Or go to Aso Volcano
或者去阿蘇火山
it's smoking
它就在冒煙
boot smoke
引導冒煙
This is a living volcano
這是就是現生的火火山
So the Great Looming is
所以大倫火山是
is alive
是活著
It looks like there is no activity
看起來沒有活動而已
Then with this result
那有了這個結果
So this is the definition of volcanology
所以這個是火山學的定義
that is
就是說
Active in ten thousand years
一萬年內有活動的
you have this record
就是你有這個紀錄的
I classify it as a volcano
我就把它歸類成火火山
just have a bad record
就是有不良紀錄的
special tube
就要特別這個列管
pay attention to it
要去注意它
This is the experience above
這是經驗上面
But the phenomenon is
但是現象是
I personally feel the phenomenon
我個人覺得現象
It doesn't have to be more scientifically meaningful.
沒必更有科學上的意義什麼
That is, if you can confirm that there is a magma chamber
就是你如果能確定有岩漿庫
like this yellowstone scientist said
就像黃石公園這個科學家說
There is a big magma chamber underneath
底下有一個好大的岩漿庫
of course it's alive
那當然是活的
If Yellowstone Park just talked about
如果以黃石公園剛剛講說
The last major eruption was 640,000 years ago
上一次噴發主要噴發是64萬年
This is very big, 10,000 years, that should be
這個很大1萬年那應該是
10 volcanic
10火山的
But Yellowstone can't use rules of thumb
可是黃石公園就不能用經驗法則
law of phenomena
就要用現象法則
It's the magma chamber that you found
就是岩漿庫你才找到
live without meaning
沒有意義就是活的
This is a general definition of something like
這是一個一般的定義上面的東西
After that with the process
那隨著過程之後
In fact, for the past five or six years
我其實過去的五六年來
every time because i do adult volcano
每次因為我做大人火山
Tell the Ministry of Science and Technology that this is a volcano
就跟科技部說這個是一個火火山
Looks like I'm a volcano
看起來是我火火山
At that time, the natural Sisi of the Ministry of Science and Technology
那時候科技部的自然思思長
Chen Yigao
陳一高
He is also the 17th of National Taiwan University
他也是台大第17的
we are still mature
我們都還滿熟
every time i meet you i say
每次碰到我就說
Lin Zheng, where are the volcanic magma chambers?
林鄭你說火火山岩漿庫在哪裡
When you meet me, ask me where the magma chamber is
碰到我就問我岩漿庫在哪裡
I was asked by him for five or six years
我就被他問了五六年
then i always wanted to talk
那我一直想講話
In fact, I probably have a spectrum how to do it
其實我大概有一個譜怎麼做
but no evidence
但是沒有證據
Then I thought
那後來就想
think of a very simple concept
想到一個很簡單的概念
Just use the shadow of the magma chamber
就是用岩漿庫的影子
The concept of this shadow is very simple
這個影子的概念就非常簡單
we see the shadow of this plane
我們看到這個飛機的影子
We don't need to look up to know
我們不用抬頭就知道
There was a plane in the sky
前空有一次飛機
Because the sun hits the plane
因為陽光碰到飛機
If you can't penetrate it, there is a shadow on the surface
穿不透就有一個影子在地表上面
it's clear
就很清楚
The X-ray on the medical
那醫學上面這個X-ray
Everyone, this X-ray hits the bone
大家都這個X-ray打過去這個骨頭
Different from tissue because of fine absorption
跟組織因為吸收細緻不一樣
So if the finger breaks off
所以指頭要是斷掉的話
see the crack
一下就看到裂痕
So this is because of the X-ray test
所以這個是因為用X光來檢驗
difference between tissue and bone
組織跟骨頭的差別
Come on, earth science actually started more than 100 years ago
來 地球科學其實在100多年前
There is such a concept that
就有這樣的概念就是說
when the earthquake happened
在地震發生的時候
Earth science has long known that
地球科學早就知道說
This external cooperation is
這個外合就是
out of code it is a liquid
out of code它是一個液態的
This is 2900 kilometers from the surface to the outside
這個從地表到外合是2900公里
is a very, very deep distance
是非常非常深的距離
But why do scientists know it's a liquid
但是科學家為什麼知道它是一個液態
It is based on the shadow of the S wave
就是根據S波的影子
Seismic waves hit the red part
地震波打到紅色的部分
you can see in this section
你在這個部分就可以看到
There is this S wave signal
有這個S波的訊號
but you have this one on the back
但是你在背面的這個
brown side
咖啡色的這邊
You can't find a straight S wave
你找不到直接的S波
because of what
因為什麼
S wave blocked by Out of Code
S波被Out of Code擋住了
It's just a liquid substance, it can't go through it.
就是液態的物質它穿不過
S waves can't penetrate
S波沒辦法穿透了
then this maybe
那這個也許
To put it simply, let me tell you
再簡單一點跟大家講就是說
This is the P wave
這是P波
when there is an earthquake
有地震的時候
Anyway, elastic waves will produce P and S
反正彈性波就會產生P跟S
This is a heavy or compression wave
這是重波或者壓縮波
it's a bump
它就是一個撞一個
Look at this black
你看這個黑色就是
it shrinks and then stretches
它縮縮然後拉張
It's like hitting a pool ball
就是好像撞球一個撞一個
So the energy is transferred in one
所以能量就一個傳遞
What is the S wave
那S波是什麼
S wave is like dead
S波就像死了一樣
it's twisted it's clipped
它是扭動的就是剪貼的
So one is a linear motion
所以一個是直線的運動
one is twisting sideways
一個是側向著扭動
This is of course simpler, for the sake of simplicity
這個當然更簡單的為了這個簡單化
That is to say, if the left side is a solid
就是說好如果左邊是個固體
on the right is a liquid
右邊是個液體
What is the difference between solid and liquid
固體跟液體有什麼不一樣
The solid is the gap between each molecule and the powder oil molecule
固體就是這個每一個分子跟粉油分子之間
Well caught by this chemical piece
被被這個化學件抓住抓得很好
it can't run around
它不能亂跑
Meaning you're on my left is on the left
意思說你在我的左邊就在左邊
you can't run to the right
你不能跑到右邊
But the liquid, the liquid, you can run as you please
但是液體的液體就隨便你跑
is liquid or gas
就是液體或氣體
It means that it doesn't have these sugar yellows, so it is gradually grasping
意思說它沒有這些糖黃就漸著抓著
So what do these two different behaviors cause?
那這兩個不同的行為會造成什麼
P4 If you turn around from this side by external force
P4你如果外力從這邊轉過來
it will
它會
it will hit this
它會這個撞這個
then this hits this
然後這個撞這個
this hit this
這個撞這個
So P4 will transfer energy
所以P4會能量會傳遞
Then you when this one comes running
那你當這一個跑過來的時候
This S wave because it has sugar yellow
這個S波因為它有糖黃
it will pull over
它會拉過來
its sugar yellow will elongate
它糖黃會拉長
so this will bring
所以這個也會帶過來
then take one by one
然後一個帶一個
So the S wave will pass like this
所以S波會傳遞這樣
So when solid
所以當固體的時候
Both P and S pass
P跟S都傳遞
but when the liquid
但是當液體
P wave is a transfer, S wave because the two have no relationship
P波是個傳遞,S波因為這兩個沒有任何的關係
So this hole will not move
所以這個洞這個不會動
To give a very simple ratio, everyone sitting here
舉一個很簡單的比例,大家坐在這邊
If we hold hands, we are solid
我們如果手拉手,就是固體
when one of them leans back
當其中有一個往後仰的話
The one next to it will also pull on it
旁邊那個也會對它拉
so it will pull one by one
所以它會一個拉一個
So this is the characteristic of S wave
所以這個就是有S波的特性
If we don't hold hands, it will be liquid
如果大家不手拉手了就是液體
one of them lay forward
其中有一個往前躺
Lean forward, the one next to it will not be disturbed
往前仰,旁邊那個它不會被干擾
is a property of solid liquids
就是固體液體的一個特性
According to this, we can test that
根據這個我們就可以來檢驗說
What kind of liquid or solid exists in the earth
地球裡面的有什麼液體或是固體的存在
just
剛剛
Well, what we imagine is that
好,那我們想像中就是說
Except for out of core, the earth is liquid outside
地球除了out of core就是外合是液體以外
Neihe , not this magma chamber
內合,而不是這個岩漿庫
It should be that the magma with high temperature is liquid
應該是有高溫的岩漿是液體的
So I was thinking that S wave will definitely disappear after hitting this point.
所以我在想說S波打到這個一定會不見吧
right
對不對
Alright, then I set up a lot of earthquake chairs here in Yangmingshan.
好 那我就在陽明山這裡就佈了很多的地震椅
Then take advantage of the very deep bottom
然後利用就是底下的很深的
We have many large and deep earthquakes off the coast of Yilan
我們在宜蘭外海很多大的深的地震
and then straight up from the bottom
然後就從底下就直接打上來
then hit our area
然後打到我們這個區域
Then I went to check which one had S wave and which one didn't.
然後我就去檢驗說哪一個有S波 哪一個沒有S波
You can see these earthquake stations in blue
你可以看到就是藍色的這些地震站
It can all see S waves
它都可以看到S波
The only areas that are red
唯一就是紅色的這些區域
it can't see s waves
它看不到S波
Of course, P wave and S wave look like everyone
那當然P波跟S波這個看起來大家
is a bit professional
是有點專業
but it's not that hard
但是也不是那麼難
I put the record of red and blue on the next one
就是我把紅色跟藍色的這個紀錄放在下一張
The following is the arrival of the P wave
下面這個就是P波到達
Then the S wave arrives and it's very clear
然後S波到達再很像很清楚
But when the seismic waves hit this magma chamber
但是當地震波打到這個岩漿庫的時候
The P wave can pass through to the S wave and cannot be found at all.
P波是可以穿到S波就完全找不到
It just disappears, disappears, and there is a shadow
就是不見了消失了就有影子
So this four-one picture means
所以這個四一圖就是說
When hitting the magma chamber, the S wave disappeared
打到岩漿庫的時候S波不見了
S wave will run out when you miss it
沒打到的時候S波就跑出來
So according to this it is simple
所以根據這個很簡單
Let's just draw a cartoon
我們就畫一個卡通圖就是
The magma chamber is here, if you hit this
岩漿庫在這邊如果打到這個
You can't see the yellow side
黃色這個側站就看不到
was blocked
就被擋住了
if this is true
如果這個是真的話
We also double-check that
我們還重複驗證就是說
If the magma chamber is here
如果岩漿庫在這裡
S waves can't pass through, but P waves
S波穿不過可是P波呢
What about heavy waves, heavy waves, solid liquids, its fine
重波呢 重波固體液體它都沒問題
it can penetrate
它都可以穿透
although it can penetrate
雖然它可以穿透
but it gets slower
可是它會變慢
because it is liquid
因為它是液態的
so it goes slower
所以它走了會比較慢
So I'll walk here together as sidekicks
所以我會一起當旁邊的走到這裡
these two it only goes here
這兩個它只有走到這裡
This is the four one picture
這是四一圖
But it's clear
但是很清楚喔
Let's see the earthquake hit here
我們看這個地震在這邊打上來
We got a signal on the surface
我們在地表收到了訊號
Then this is simulated
然後這個是模擬
If you hit the magma chamber here it will slow down
你如果打到岩漿庫這裡就會變慢
Then the S wave disappeared
然後S波不見
On the right hand side is our observation
右手邊就是我們觀測
The distance that will be written every time a wave hits the magma chamber
每打到岩漿庫的波就會寫的距離
in this dark place
在這個黑的地方
will appear here to arrive
會出現這邊到達
But as soon as you hit the magma door
但是一打到岩漿戶
it won't be here
它不會在這裡
it's a little slow
是慢了一點點
So you look at the S wave and don't see it
所以你看S波又不見
Then the P wave is tired again
然後P波又頂累
for me
對我來講
this is no doubt space
這是毫無懷疑的空間
There is a liquid substance under the ground
就是地底下有一個液態的物質
The liquid substance has said
那液態的物質有說
Not necessarily magma or water
不見得是岩漿是水
That's impossible
那不可能
Why
為什麼
At 20 kilometers the water will be squeezed out
在20公里水會被擠出來
magma
岩漿
Its density is closer to that of stone
它的密度跟石頭比較接近
it can be kept
它才可以保留
so it can't be water
所以不可能是水
Of course magma is the best and only explanation
當然岩漿是最好的唯一的解釋
Then its size is about
那它的大小大概就是
GOO!
GOO啦
70 square kilometers
70平方公里
How big is 70 square kilometers
70平方公里大概多大
is its area
就是它的面積
About a quarter of the size of the administrative district of Taipei City
大概四分之一個台北市的行政區大小
Let's all do something
讓大家有點乾的
A little bigger than Siling District
比四陵區大一點
It is slightly smaller than Xinyi Songshan Nangang in the East District
比東區的新義松山南港稍微小一點點
what's the point of this
那這個有什麼意義呢
As long as a region of a local kilometer
只要一個地方公里的一個地區
so come on lava
所以在岩漿上來
probably just like
大概就跟
The pavement is so big before reaching Pinya
還沒有到品牙就鋪得那麼大
possible to st seabee st helens
可能到聖海比聖海倫
erupt a little bigger
噴發的大一點點
that would be terrible
那就超可怕的
so instead of saying
所以不是說
All this magma goes to the surface
所有這些岩漿都會報地表
Actually it's only 1%
其實它只要1%
a percentage to the surface
一個百分比的到地表
In fact, the volcano will erupt
其實就會火山噴發
It's dangerous and powerful
就很危險很厲害
Well, of course this is
好 那這個當然就
Because of the results of these studies
因為這些研究的結果
So the central
所以中央就
except the legislature
除了立法院
Then the Executive Yuan
然後行政院
have done some coping with this
有做了一些這個應對
So elegant planning for volcanic disasters
所以火山災害的優雅計畫
no matter central place now
現在不管中央地方
must follow above
都要follow上面
Some mechanisms of this strain
這個應變的一些機制
good though
好 雖然
find the magma chamber
把岩漿庫找出來
but for me
可是對我來講
In fact, the challenge is greater
其實挑戰更大
The reason is that this is
原因是這個是
What we call Huang Xinhua
我們所謂的黃信華
this colleague did
這個同事做的
at this
在這個
Made by Huang's Park
這個黃氏公園做的
There's a magma chamber under it
它底下有個岩漿庫
there is a
上面有一個
that's in taiwan
那在台灣
I think it's 20 kilometers
我覺得在20公里
what we see is this
我們看到的是這個
In fact, I am more worried about whether there is a potential
其實更擔心這潛的有沒有
Because our resolution is limited
因為我們的解析度有限
so I dare not speak
所以我也不敢講說
Does the upper crust have
上部地殼有沒有
So the Ministry of Science and Technology gave me an order to continue looking for
所以科技部就給我一個命令說繼續找
Let's come up with a big plan
我們就提一個滿大的計畫
At the ninth month they are
在第九個月期的他們就
We are in the secret spicy earthquake war in northern Taiwan
我們就在北台灣部的祕密麻辣地震戰
I hope that Minister Hill and Guishan Island
希望把大臣山還有貴山島
Find it in the magma chambers of these two volcanoes
這兩個火山的岩漿庫把它找出來
In fact, we also found the magma chamber on Guishan Island.
那貴山島的岩漿庫其實我們也找出來
The article is under review
文章正在審稿
should be out soon
應該很快就會出來
So there is definitely a magma reservoir under Guishan
所以貴山的底下也明確有一個岩漿庫
So we want to take this size depth
所以我們希望把這個大小深度
Hope to find it out
位置希望都把它找出來
So I hope to finish this project in four years
所以希望四年時間把這個計畫做完
This is the black street station of our first year department
這是我們第一年部的黑色的街站
Then the next year I hope to fill the white
然後第二年希望把白色的填滿
Then the third year and the fourth year
然後第三年第四年
I can actually do some analysis and research
我就可以真正的去做一些分析研究
good
好
Next is this TVO
接下來就是這個TVO
this volcano
這個火山
looks alive
看起來是活的
eruption cannot be ruled out
噴發不能排除
what shall we do
那我們怎麼辦
This fear is often rooted in ignorance
這個恐懼常常就是因為無知
This is the Aso volcano just mentioned in Japan
這是日本的剛剛講的阿蘇火山
There are railroad houses and a lot of residents inside.
裡面有鐵軌房子什麼居民一大堆
This is a big crater
這是好大一個火山口
people live in it
人就住在裡面
Lived for decades or hundreds of years, maybe a thousand years
住了幾十年幾百年搞不好千年了
they didn't panic
他們也沒有恐慌
live inside the crater
就住在火山口裡面
where is the reason
那原因在哪裡
This one is more interesting
這一張更有意思
This is the eruption of Xiahao clam on May 1st
這個是夏浩蜊五月一噴發
Director Chen of the NCD
那個NCD那個陳主任就
just send me this one and say wow this one
把這一張就寄給我說哇這個
super nice look
超好你看
This old beauty seems very handsome
這老美好像很帥
The volcano is covered in ashes
火山已經滿天的灰了
He also raised his voice over there
他一樣在那邊打高了呼求
The reason is that they are not afraid
原因是他們可不怕
The reason not to be afraid is not because you have courage
不怕的原因不是說很有勇氣
because of something
因為有什麼
with this backing
有這個靠山
This is the station of Xiahaoli Volcano Pass
這是夏浩蜊火山關這站
Bottom this next to this
底下這個旁邊這個
less than 100 meters
不到一百公尺就
When I visited last year, I asked him
我去年去訪問的時候問他說
How deep is your crater along the river?
你們這個火山口沿江多深
He said three kilometers
他說三公里
I said three kilometers, how dare you live here
我說三公里你們還敢住在這邊
This has a history of 100 years
這個已經有100年的歷史
Why
為什麼
Volcanic eruption will not be instant
火山要噴發不會瞬間
There will be actions and warnings
會有動作會有預警
So they can have a good grasp
所以他們就可以掌握得很好
so they pass
所以他們透過
Earth science regardless of the air
地球科學的不管空中
All kinds of monitoring on the surface or underground
地表或地下的各式各樣監測
as long as there is movement
只要有動的話
we can
我們就能夠
before the volcano erupts
火山要噴發之前
there should be
應該就會有
just like Visway's
像剛剛維斯威的
This is the oldest
這個是前之最老的
This one existed in 1841
這個1841年就有了
This is a very old painting
這是很老很老的畫的
that is the status quo
那是現狀
this
這個
Isn't Pompeii already destroyed?
龐貝不是已經被蓋掉了
Why is there still a volcanic view on the station?
為什麼還要有火山觀在站
someone is
有人是
sorry
對不起
pompeii in
龐貝在
South of Wesway
維斯威的南邊
To the north of him is Napolis
他的北邊還有納波里斯
So this also needs to be Watched
所以這個也要Watch
to observe
要觀測
another day
另外哪一天
this volcano will
這個火山會
It's bad luck for these people to come here
這些人來這邊就倒霉了
so they have to monitor
所以他們要做監測
So we are at Datong Volcano
所以我們在大同火山
We're going to set up an observatory
我們要成立一個觀測站
This is the hardware provided by the teaching staff of Yang Mingzhang
這是楊明章國教工也提供的硬體
it's a nice environment
這是一個還不錯的環境
we borrowed here
我們在這邊借了
Four or five Office
四五個Office
Then build this observatory
然後再建這個觀測站
good
好
At the beginning, the Ministry of Science and Technology and the Ministry of the Interior
當初就科技部跟內政部
Because national industry belongs to the Ministry of the Interior
因為國家工業屬於內政部
We have a MEMO
我們就有一個MEMO
and then construct this
然後就建構這個
So the Ministry of Science and Technology paid the main money
所以科技部出了主要的錢
Our Chinese is also the main person
我們中文也是出了主要的人
not only me
不是只有我
Many technicians at our Earth Institute
我們地球所的很多技術人員
researchers participate in
研究人員就參與
Ministry of Science and Technology
科技部
The hardware equipment produced by the Ministry of the Interior
這個內政部就出的硬體設備
Out of electricity, out of the house, out of these air conditioners
出電 出房子 出這些冷氣
so we just
所以我們就
Because this is not actually a
因為這個其實不是一個
Very simple one unit can perform
很簡單的一個單位可以執行的
So we integrated a lot of
所以我們就整合了很多的
That's where our observatory's instruments are located
那這就是我們的觀測站的儀器分布的位置
That's the triangular fault just mentioned
那這是剛剛講的三角斷層
This is the entire area of Yangmingshan
這是整個陽明山的區域
Conceptually this picture is us on the surface
概念上這張圖就是我們在地表上面
Many different instruments were deployed
佈了很多不同的儀器
Includes seismographs, crustal deformation, geochemistry, geothermal jets
包括地震儀、地殼變形、地球化學、地溫噴氣
I always hope that as long as the volcano has erupted before
總總是希望說只要火山有噴發之前
We believe that there should be some anomalies in these
我們相信這些應該都會有一些異常
Then we have to report to the government, the people and everyone.
那我們就要跟政府跟民眾跟大家報告
Said the volcano may have started to restless
說火山可能已經開始不安分
That's our real-time monitoring station
那這是我們即時的監測站
So we send a lot of real-time news to this screen for discussion
所以我們把很多即時的就傳到這個螢幕上面做討論
Then this picture is the enlarged one just now
那這張圖就是剛剛那個放大
This four-one picture is if people go up
這四一圖就是人家如果往上竄
In fact, the surface and the crust will deform, right?
其實地表就會、地殼就會變形對不對
be raised or arched
被台升或者拱起來
We'll just lean on the GPS to level the camp
我們就靠GPS傾斜以後水準營
we can measure the deformation of its crust
我們就可以量它的地殼變形的
And then here's like volcanic gas
然後這邊像火山的氣體
Because its concentration composition will also change
因為它的濃度成分也會改變
It is conceivable that the temperature will also increase
溫度可想而知也會增高
special seismic activity
特別地震活動
Because my special session is doing earthquake activities
因為我的專場是做地震活動
seismic activity is
地震活動是
Of course I know best
我當然懂得最多
and I believe the most useful
而且我相信應該是最有用的
a concept map
一個概念圖
I dont know if its usually 10 kilometers or 20 kilometers along the river.
平常沿江那邊10公里 20公里不知道
Because there is heat along the river
因為沿江有熱
So there's a little bit of an earthquake on it
所以它上面就有一些少許的地震
But if you run from A to B along the river like this
但是沿江像這個從A跑到B的話
Only along the river will you run up
沿江才會跑上來
what will happen to this incredible thing
這不得了的事情會發生什麼
Due to the change of temperature and pressure above
上面因為溫度壓力的改變
There will be many, many earthquakes
會產生很多很多的地震
For example
舉例來講
Our Yangmingshan is now a month
我們陽明山現在一個月
There may be only 3 or 5 earthquakes every day
每天可能只有3個5個地震而已
If you run up the river
如果沿江往上跑的話
i predict or i imagine
我預測或者我想像
There may be 500 to 1000 earthquakes in one day
一天可能500個1000個地震
That's obviously different
那就很明顯的不一樣
Our record map secretly shows earthquakes
我們那個紀錄圖就秘密跑的都是地震
But when you see it, it means that there is a follow-up action
但是看到的時候代表就是有後續的動作
when it goes up
那它越往上的時候
This is called a volcanic eruption.
這個到地表才叫火山噴發嘛
But you can say from B to C
但是你可以想說從B到C
this earthquake
這地震
At B, the earthquake may be 3 kilometers away
B的時候地震可能3公里
1 kilometer left at C
到C的時候剩下1公里
Here maybe 5 kilometers or 10 kilometers
在這裡也許是5公里或10公里
what does this mean
這代表什麼
We only need the depth of the earthquake to determine it
我們只要地震的深度把它定出來
Must slowly change from deep to front
一定從深的慢慢變前
it's maybe 20 days from here to here
它從這裡到這裡也許是20天
I know it runs 0.5 kilometers a day
我知道它每天跑0.5公里
If it is 3 days from here to here
這裡到這裡如果是3天
I just saw it run 0.2km a day or something
我才看到它每天跑0.2公里或多少
can i estimate
我可以預估嗎
I guess it's okay
我就估算就是說好
That could be 10 days or a week to the surface
那可能到地表可能剩下10天或一個禮拜
so i can't tell you guys
所以我不能告訴大家說說
Will there be a volcanic eruption next year?
明年會不會有火山噴發
this time is too far
這個時間太遠
I can't follow
我沒辦法跟
but
但是
But if say a month the volcano will
但是如果說一個月火山會
Volcano erupts in a month
一個月火山會噴發
I am sure I will see the exception
我相信我一定會看到異常
I'll see a spike in these earthquakes
我會看到這些地震的暴增
Of course it's not just an earthquake.
當然不是靠地震而已啦
That is, the volcanic gas immediately deforms
就是火山氣體立刻變形
Low temperature, there should always be abnormalities in this
低溫 總總這個應該都會有異常
When integrated, there should be good information to judge
整合起來應該會有很好的資訊去判斷
That also means that this is the approximate timeline
那同樣就是說這是大概時間軸
I can roughly estimate how long it might take to reach the surface
我大概可以預估可能多久會到地表
Similarly, if I see Huangzui Mountain
同樣我如果看到是黃嘴山
Earthquakes are coming out of Huangzui Mountain
地震都在黃嘴山冒出來
I don't know that Huangzui Mountain may be delayed and approach the surface
不知道黃嘴山可能延將快到地表
If it is in Dayoukeng
如果是在大遊坑
I'm a big travel pit
我就是大遊坑可能延將存存易動
so i know something
所以我知道點
Then if I see big tour pit and small tour pit
那如果我看到大遊坑 小遊坑
Why is Huangzuishan what city?
怎麼黃嘴山什麼都市的話
The representative said wow, it was serious
代表說哇 之下子就嚴重了
it's frontal, right?
它是前面性的對不對
So the size time
所以規模大小時間
Probably scientifically, I can make an estimate
大概科學上面我可以去做預估
So we did a lot of observations
所以我們就做了很多的觀測
But of course there have been no volcanic eruptions so far
但是至今為止當然沒有火山噴發
it's very lucky
這是非常幸運的事情
but we
但是我們
even without a volcanic eruption
即使沒有火山噴發
we do scientific research
我們做科學研究
We still found a lot of interesting things
我們還是發現好多有趣的事情
what is interesting
什麼叫有趣
We are Earthquake Warfare
我們就是地震戰
I will talk about the earthquake part
我就講地震的部分
this is
這個就是
Each line is a record of 24 hours a day
每一條線就是一天24小時的記錄
A black is 15 minutes
一條黑色是15分鐘
then blue for an hour
然後藍色就一個小時
2 hours 24 hours
兩個小時24小時
Show you 45 hours in the middle of the night
給你看到半夜45個小時
The ground is shaking
這個地表一直在震動
First I saw this 10 years ago
一開始我10年前看到這個
I just want to say
我就想說
that is the car
那就是車子
what windswept hole
什麼風吹潮洞
Anyway, there are many people in Yangmingshan
反正陽明山就很多人
but i want to say
但是我想說
The time pair is 10 o'clock in the middle of the night
時間一對是半夜10點到
2:30 am
早上凌晨2點3點
impossible to have a car
不可能有車子
unless it's something weird
除非是很詭異的事情
That's science
那以科學上面
we certainly believe
我們當然相信是
believe in science
相信科學
So there should be no human activity
所以應該不會有人為活動
That should be this natural phenomenon
那應該就是這個自然的現象
Because if the pot is heating it up,
因為鍋子如果在把它燒加熱的話
when the pressure builds
壓力變大的時候
The lid of the pot is not related to the steam
鍋蓋不是就會蒸氣的關係
will it be a vibration
它就會是震動嗎
The vibration is likely to be caused by
震動很可能就是造成
The concept that the entire surface of the earth is shaking
整個地表在震動的概念
That's also very interesting
那這個也是非常有意思
This is also an earthquake station
這也是某一個地震站
is one two three four
是一個兩個三個四個
Just look at a dozen earthquake stations
就是你看十幾個地震站
send a signal at the same time
都同時寄到一個訊號
Then this signal is called to look like a drop
然後這個訊號叫做看起來是水滴狀
This is the water drop shape in the scientific community
這是科學界就用水滴狀的
an earthquake record
一個地震紀錄
This is similar to the Chiayi Hualian earthquake
這個跟比如說嘉義華聯的地震
completely different shape
形狀完全不一樣
Chiayi Hualian these earthquakes look
嘉義華聯這些地震看起來
We look at P waves, S waves, and tangential body circles
我們看P波、S波、切像體圈
They all do this every day
他們都每天在做這個
But this one can't see the P wave at all
但這個完全看不到P波
S wave sees one
S波就看到一個
It's just a very special energy in the shape of a water drop.
很特殊的像水滴狀的一個能量而已
Then if you look closely at its frequency
那你如果仔細看它的頻率的話
that's more interesting
那更有趣
it is single frequency
它是單頻的
it's about three to a few hertz
它是大概三點幾赫茲的
single frequency signal
就是單頻的訊號
How can there be a single-frequency signal in nature?
大自然的怎麼會有單頻的訊號呢
this is incredible
這是很不可思
Of course it's simple. We want to say that everyone has played an instrument.
當然很簡單我們想說大家玩過樂器
If you strip one of the strings, its a single fret, right?
你如果剝其中一條弦都是單品對不對
That means it looks like someone is stripping a string in the ground
那代表說地底下好像有人在剝一條弦
Of course it's impossible
這當然不可能的事情嘛
Well, the real reason is
那其實真正的原因是喔
Because the magma under the ground actually has these cracks
因為地底下這些岩漿它其實有這些裂縫
When the gas or liquid in these cracks
當這些裂縫的氣體或者液體
It just needs a change in pressure or a quick movement
它只要壓力的改變或者快速的移動
the whole rock wall will shake
那整個岩壁就會搖晃
The frequency of shaking is determined by its width and length
搖晃的頻率就是看它的寬度長度決定
like stripping a string
就像剝一條弦那樣
If the thickness and length of its strings are fixed
它的弦的粗細長短固定的話
its frequency is fixed
它的頻率就固定
the width of the crack
那個岩縫的寬
Its geometry is the same it is a single frequency
它的幾何一樣它就單一個頻率
Then this is our real interpretation
那這個就是真正的我們的解釋
It also has a shape like a screw
那也有像螺絲釘狀
super image screw
超像螺絲釘
called english they called Tonillos
叫做英文他們叫Tonillos
this is
這個是
This is very famous
這個是非常有名喔
Anyone who knows about volcanic earthquakes
火山地震的人都知道
Why
為什麼
In Central America just those volcanoes
在中美洲剛剛那些火山
when they often erupt
他們常常噴發的時候
just see this first
就先看到這個
How long does it take for the volcano to erupt after seeing this allergy?
看到這個過敏多久火山就噴發
So this becomes
所以這個變成是
an indicator of a volcano in central america
中美洲火山的一個指標
but can't say
但是也不能說
Taiwan sees this volcanic eruption
台灣看到這個火山噴發
Because different volcanoes behave differently
因為不同的火山的行為不一樣
some volcanic properties
有些火山的特性
can be used as a reference
是可以當參考
But what we saw on Dalun Mountain
但是大倫山我們看到的
Doesn't mean the volcano is going to erupt
不是代表火山要噴發
but it represents
但是它代表是
Some properties of volcano activity
火山的一些活動的特性
Then it's more interesting to see how often
然後你看它的頻率更有意思
It is 2.1 4.2 6.3 8.4
它是2.1 4.2 6.3 8.4
just a few special ones
就是特殊的幾個
This multiplied signal is just
這個倍頻的訊號而已
Of course this is also a metaphor
那當然這個也是個比喻
like this
就好像這個
You went to pluck the pipa and plucked three strings
你去撥琵琶撥了三條弦
Three different frequencies come out
三個不同的頻率就出來了
Of course there can't be
那當然底下不可能有
these choices
這些情選
the same is
同樣就是
you also have a
你同時有一個
extended to different enshrining times
延長到不同的列奉的時候
A column Bong is a frequency
A列奉是一個頻率
Column B is the frequency of series Bong
B列奉是系列奉的頻率
it has since been blown to words
它從此被吹給的話
When you bite it, it will come out with some fixed frequency
咬起來它就有固定的一些頻率出來
that also has this low frequency
那也有這個低頻的
In fact, its frequency is very low
其實它的頻率很低
That's also very classic
那這個也是非常經典
The usual breakthrough volcanic eruption just mentioned
剛剛講的平常突破的火山噴發
Do it for me on January 17th
1月17日幫我做
About 10 days before the eruption
在火山噴發的前10天左右
they see these things
他們看到這些東西
Hundreds of low-frequency earthquakes came out
幾百個低頻的地震跑出來
then finally they explained
那最後他們解釋說
When the magma runs in the cracks of the rock
當岩漿在岩縫裡面跑的時候
low frequency signal
就會產生低頻的訊號
So it's also a good indicator
所以這也是很好的指標
if dalun chapter we see a lot of this
如果大倫章我們看到很多這個的話
It's also a big warning sign
也是很大的一個警訊
There is also this Cheung Chau class
那也有這個長洲級的
In fact, there are quite a lot of pigs of this kind.
其實豬的此類其實非常的多
I will speed up a little bit
我就稍微加快一點點
Okay, then let's take the original chairperson
好 那我們就把當初的主委
this confession
這個交代的事情
Academician Li Rouxuan
這個李柔璇院士
Later, our Institute of Earth Sciences
後來也是我們地球科學所
Rescue director
營救所所長
After he is here as the chief committee member,
他在這邊這個主委下來以後
Let's finish this Volcano Watching Station
我們把這個火山觀世站完成
Of course, the mission of the Volcano Watching Station is mainly for volcanic disasters
當然火山觀世站的任務主要是火山災害
But it actually seems to be a negative
但是其實這好像是負面
But there are also positive
但是其實也有一些正面
This volcanic resource, geothermal development
這個火山資源啊 地熱開發
In fact, they are two sides of the same body.
其實都是一體的兩面
If we take these magma
我們如果把這些岩漿啊
These geothermal surveys are clear
這些地熱調查很清楚
In fact, it can be applied
其實都可以應用
Are those two Yamadas successful?
那兩名山大大產收析嘛
what is the back garden
就是什麼 後花園
very beautiful natural landscape
非常漂亮的自然景觀
that also has fumaroles
那也有火山的噴氣孔
The hole of exile is a landscape unique to these volcanoes
流亡孔這些火山特有的景觀
different time periods
不同的時段
Huang Wen during the day
黃溫白天
very beautiful
非常的美
These are some photos taken by our TVO colleagues over there
這都是我們TVO的同事在那邊拍的一些照片
It has snowed in the past two years
最近兩年也下了雪
It's also very rare
這也是非常難得的
Snow scene throughout our TVO
整個我們TVO的雪景
that hot spring
那溫泉
After having these beautiful landscapes
有這些漂亮的這些景觀以後
if again
如果再
Development of hot springs Development of Sidan
溫泉的開發 四淡的開發
An area that can provide better tourism, leisure and vacation
可以提供更好的旅遊 休閒度假的一個區域
That's these snow monkeys in Hokkaido, Japan
那就是日本的北海道的這些雪猴
They also know to take a hot spring when it's cold
他們也知道很冷的時候要泡溫泉
The largest geothermal development is Iceland
那最大的地熱開發就是冰島
In fact, besides enjoying these hot springs, Iceland
冰島其實他們除了享受這些溫泉以外
They are also the world's geothermal development
他們也是全世界把地熱開發
Probably more than 80% of Iceland's energy is geothermal.
大概冰島的能源大概八成以上都是地熱
so they don't need a nuclear power plant
所以他們不需要核能廠
Nuclear power plants don't need to burn coal
核能廠不需要燒煤
they enjoy the natural
他們就享受這天然的
Since Taiwan has these volcanic geothermal
那台灣既然有這些火山地熱
In fact, we should do some work on the concept
其實概念上面我們應該往這邊做一些工作
So will continental volcanoes have geothermal development?
那所以大陸火山會不會有地熱開發
In addition to this volcanic construction
除了這個火山建設以外
In fact, I also spent some time doing these tasks.
其實我也花了一些心思在做這些的工作
We put up some seismic stations that look like
我們擺了一些地震站看起來在
There seems to be a big one here
在這裡好像有一個很大的一個
Hot discussion storage area
熱議儲存區
If the science above this should be specifically
如果科學上面這應該專
Earthquake opening should be a good place
地震開放應該是個好地方
But don't believe it's in a national park
不過不信它是在國家公園裡面
This environmental protection regulation may also design customer service
這個環保的法規可能還要設計客服
But anyway this is
不過anyway這個是
Anyway, based on science, we can do some related things
反正以科學上面我們可以做一些相關的事情
good
好
The map part is more fun
地圖部分就是比較好玩的
this voice
這個要這個聲音
This is actually the media or something
這個其實媒體或者什麼
you may have the impression
你們可能有印象
say in a while
過一陣子就說
someone heard a strange sound
有人聽到怪聲音
then this is
那這就是
15 years is
15年的就是
someone heard something
有人聽到什麼什麼
anyway some description
反正一些描述
it means sound
就是有聲音的意思
someone over here heard
這邊有人聽到
In fact, when the media came to ask us
其實當初媒體來問我們
Actually, I probably have a clue
其實我大概有譜
But at that time it was not well organized
但是那時候還沒有整理很好
so just pretend not to know
所以就假裝不知道
But now I probably know
但現在就大概都知道了
also in history
歷史上也有
You see, this is 1835 and 53 years
這個你看就是1835年53年的時候
next day big butt
下日大臀
three days
三明三日
it will be very noisy
就是會很吵很吵吵
then we
那我們
Since we do these our TBO colleagues
自從我們做這些我們TBO的同事
Now I often call and say
現在常常會打電話說
The teacher often hears place names today
老師今天常常有聽到地名
It's just that some people can hear it and some people can't.
就是有些人聽得到有些人聽不到
of course you really
那當然你實在
some say some don't
有些人說有些人沒有
is there any
到底是有沒有
this
這個
we rely on evidence
我們靠證據
There are of course many reasons for place names
地名當然有很多原因
There are places with earthquakes and various guitars
有地震的地名有吉他各式各樣
Today we will talk about the place names of volcanoes
我們今天就講火山的地名
This is our sacrifice
這是我們祭道
this is about five minutes long
這個大概有五分鐘長
but I say it as
但是我把它說成
probably no more than five seconds
大概沒比五秒鐘而已
the reason is because
原因是因為
when everyone listens for five minutes
當大家聽五分鐘
probably fell asleep
可能就睡著了
The first reason is to say
第一個原因是說
if five minutes ago
如果五分鐘前
In fact, its frequency is very low
其實它那個頻率很低
you can't hear
你聽不到
because our ears are from
因為我們耳朵是從
20Hz to 20,000Hz
20Hz到2萬Hz
normal person
正常人
If it is 10Hz
如果是10Hz
we can't hear
我們聽不到
just too low frequency
就是太低頻
or too high frequency
或者太高頻
So for everyone to hear
所以為了讓大家聽到
I'll take it a little
我就把它稍微
This is called a dead sound
這個叫做縮死聲音
turn five minutes into five seconds
把它五分鐘變成五秒鐘
this is overclocking
這個是超頻
But the five flavors are like a plane flying past
但五味的就好像飛機飛過去而已
but
但是
We use these signals
我們根據這些訊號
Actually, you see, this is a different kind of earthquake warfare
其實你看這是不同的地震戰
Why Earthquake Warfare Receives Sound
為什麼地震戰會受到聲音
In fact, the sound is the vibration of air
其實聲音就是空氣震動
air shaken to the surface
空氣震動到的地表
our ruins on the surface
我們的遺跡放在地表
Shake our relics too
也會搖我們的遺跡
because of shaking the ground
因為搖地面
shake relics
搖遺跡
So let's remember the signals
所以我們去記到這些訊號
We can see these earthquake shadows
這些地震影我們就看起來
You see this is every earthquake video received
你看這個就是每個地震影都收到
Then we according to its sequence
然後我們根據它的先後
we can go and find out where it is
我們可以去找出它的位置
Like this example, we found it in Xiaoniu Pit
像這個例子我們找出來就是在小牛坑
very clear
非常清楚
I don't know if it's here or here
不知道在這裡還是這裡
perhaps
大概
The difference may be 10 meters 50 meters
差可能10公尺 50公尺
but not going outside the calf pit
但是不會跑到小牛坑的外頭去
anyway
反正
Shanhui is also here
山會也在這裡就是
Sure
確定
This is just about one hundred and two minutes
這個就是剛剛也是大概一百兩分鐘
I put it like two seconds
我把它說成大概兩秒
you will hear
你就聽到
Actually look carefully at this
這個其實你仔細看
In fact, this picture alone wrote an article on this
這個其實這個光這張圖就寫了一篇這個
This scientific international article
這個這個科學性的國際文章
I talked about this this is
我就談到這個這個是
this is time
這個是時間
this is the frequency
這是頻率
This is when the whole thing explodes
這個是整個像爆炸的時候
before the explosion
然後爆炸之前
It has frequencies from seventy grammes all the way down to almost forty grammes
它有頻率從七十克子一直掉掉到差不多四十克子
The frequency keeps going back and forth
頻率就一直遞解遞解
then give it a blast
然後就給爆炸
Actually very simple description
其實很簡單的描述
It's like playing that heavy sky cannon when I was a child
就好像小時候玩那個重天炮
You chirp at one point and it explodes in the sky
你一點就啾然後天空中炸開來
That's certainly not a heavy sky cannon
那當然不是重天炮
This actually has good physics behind it
這其實它有背後有很好的物理
Then we probably don't have time to talk about deeper things.
那我們大概沒時間講比較深的東西
In fact, Xiaoerkeng often records these things
小兒坑其實就常常就會記錄到這些事情
That child's pit is more interesting
那小兒坑更有意思
This is the location of the children's pit
這個是小兒坑的位置
You went to Xiaoerkeng to play Qiqisan and climbed up
你往小兒坑玩七七三爬上去的
this is the trail
這是步道
You can see these little pits along the trail
你可以沿著步道看到這一個一個的小坑
Then it actually becomes a series of cracks
然後其實就串成一系列的裂縫
How did these cracks come about?
那這些裂縫 怎麼來了
In fact, I know how some place names come from.
其實有的地名我就知道是怎麼來的
Actually this is every
其實這是每一個
It was just the result of the explosion that looked like Chongtian helping him
就剛剛那個像蟲天幫他爆炸的結果
I mean this small pit
意思說 這個小坑
Of course not with time
當然不是與時砸下去
In turn it is a gas explosion from within
反過來它是從內部的氣爆
It's when there's a lot of pressure underneath
就是底下的壓力很大的時候
It instantly exploded like a hole
它瞬間像爆炸一樣 炸開來就是一孔
So it's just a hole along this fault line
所以它沿著這個斷裂帶就一個孔
hole by hole
一個孔一個孔就是
geological age has been
地質年代就一直在
explode again
再炸開來
That's how it stays on the surface
那留著地表就是成這樣
So if you examine this entire fracture hole
那你如果檢視這個整個斷裂孔
These are all one by one
都是一個一個細的這些
It seems that this is connected with those in Shikeng
好像這個與時坑的這些連起來的
very very many
非常非常多
The rep says it's actually been active
代表說它其實一直在活動
It's just that we haven't paid attention to it
只是我們一直沒注意它而已
Generally speaking, we say that volcanic eruptions are magma.
那一般我們講說火山噴發就是岩漿
Like this steam explosion just looks like that explosion sound that's it
像這種蒸氣爆炸就剛剛看起來那種爆炸的聲音就是這樣
Then this kind is like Hawaii, or many of them are hot sun to the surface with lava and broken rust flow
那這種就是像夏威夷啊或者很多就是炎陽到地表有熔岩有碎鏽流
What about this one? It's like Kaohsiung gas explosion
那這種是怎樣?它就是像高雄氣爆那樣
It explodes, only the power of this door's cauldron explodes
炸開來,只有這個門燒鍋炸開來的力量而已
Then don't say it doesn't seem threatening.
那你不要說這個好像沒什麼威脅性
January 3, 2014 he was a steam explosion
2014的1月3日他就是一個蒸氣爆炸
He also caused the deaths of more than 60 people
他也造成了60幾個人的死亡
That death is really unfortunate
那這個死亡實在是很不幸的是
this is autumn, then noon, then it's saturday
這個是秋天,然後是中午,然後他是星期六
Because this January 3rd is like our Central Mountain Range, there are usually no people living nearby
因為這1月3日就像我們的中環山脈,平常都附近都沒住人
But the autumn wind is also super beautiful, a bunch of people went hiking on Saturday
但是秋天風也超漂亮,星期六一堆人去爬山
Then when they run to the top of the mountain, their habit is to go to the top of the mountain
然後跑到山頂的時候,他們的習慣就到山頂的時候
You have to go to the top of the mountain before noon, and come down after eating some steam or bento
中午以前要到山頂,吃個蒸氣或便當就下來
Everyone near noon is at 3
快到中午的所有人都在3點
As a result, the explosion at that time
結果那時候的爆炸
That's why sixty or seventy
所以才會造成六七十個
if he is monday
如果他是星期一
or 3 p.m.
或者是下午3點
a cat is fine
一隻貓都沒事
this is such an unfortunate thing
這就是這麼不幸的事情
just listen to this
這個就聽聽
This is two when we count
這是兩名當我們計到的
You said it sounded like a bird chirping
你說很像鳥叫聲
like the people of the forest
就是好像樹林的人
this one is slightly longer
這個稍微長一點的
about two minutes
大概有兩分鐘左右
In fact, I have collected a lot of these
其實我就收集了好多好多這個
no i can't come in
不行 我不能進來
This is like a train
這個是好像火車
played the sound of a train
演出了火車的聲音
This image is staring at me
這個像在巨視我
that's good
這樣就好了
Then this giant viewer just now actually
然後這個剛剛那個巨視戶其實
From now on I will write another article
從此我要寫另外一個文章
Just talking about this is a volcano conversation.
就談這個就是火山的對話
In fact, it is one by one
其實它這一條一條就是
This Jet Arch Happened Another is this one
這個噴氣拱發生另外就是這一個
So A and B are over there
所以A跟B兩個就在那邊
It's super fun to sing along
一搭一唱的超有趣的
It's the dialogue of the volcano
就是火山的對話
Then this is Zhongshan Luo and Ziping after spraying
然後這個就是中山羅噴完就跟子平
Then it's like the two are talking
然後就是好像兩個在對話
The last one is
最後這個是
Dean Guoyu
國瑜院長
This is a piece of Dean Guoyu
這個是一塊是國瑜院長
I'll skip it first
我先把它跳過去
That's Dean Guoyu
那是國瑜院長
See me these volcano sounds
看到我這些火山的聲音
He went to find that one called Art Association
他就去找那個那個那個叫做藝術協院
This is the performance art
就是這個表演藝術的
He said this voice can be used as background
他說這個聲音可以當背景
Then they played for two hours
然後他們就演了兩個小時
Then I listen to this wow this is wonderful
然後我去聽這種哇這個真精彩
This is the combination of science and humanities
這就這個科學與人文的結合
good last volcano heartbeat
好最後火山心跳
Then we have SeismicNet and we can record a lot of earthquakes
那我們有地震網我們就記了很多的地震
That earthquake was nothing special
那地震沒什麼了不起
But the funny thing is that we are here in Dayoukeng
但是好玩的就是我們在大遊坑這裡
recorded hundreds of earthquakes
記了幾百個地震
So what's so special about this earthquake?
那這個地震有什麼特意呢
This is the new electrogram
這是新電圖
Then every black line here is
那這裡每一條黑黑的就是
This one is an earthquake station
這個一個就是一個地震站
Then every earthquake will have a
那每一個地震同時都會有一個
just an earthquake
就是有一個地震
So when an earthquake occurs
所以一個地震發生的時候
Received all the brochures
就所有的冊單都收到
Then this bar and bar is an earthquake
那這個一槓一槓的就是一個地震
For example, just look at a single one.
那比如說看單一的就好
single brochure you see
單一的冊單你看
When each vertical bar
這每一個垂直槓的時候
just a small earthquake
就是一個小地震發生
Then this small earthquake turned out to be periodic
然後這個小地震它竟然是周期性
Hualian earthquake
化聯發生地震
probably no one can understand
大概沒有人可以理解說
when will the next earthquake occur
下一個地震哪時候發生
but here i go with you
但是在這裡我去跟你們
Now there's another 18 minutes
現在有個18分鐘就有另外一個
At 18 minutes, here are the statistics
在18分鐘,這裡做統計
Of course not by a few seconds
當然不是有幾秒的誤差
There will be one in 18 or 19 minutes
那18、19分鐘就有來一個
This is about 1, 200 earthquakes
這大概一、200個地震
every 18 minutes
每18分鐘就來一下子
We know our heartbeat is 7, 80 beats per minute
我們知道我們的心跳是每分鐘7、80下
But you count about 18 minutes, 7, 80 times a day
可是你算18分鐘大概,每天7、80下
This means it dances very slowly
這個意思說它跳得非常慢
But it is more interesting to say, when did this heartbeat start
但是更有意思是說,這個心跳從哪時候開始
It is from a 4.8 earthquake in Hualien
它是從一個花蓮的4.8的地震
When the earthquake reached Yang Mingshan
那地震播到楊明山的時候
Then the heart starts beating
那心跳就開始跳了
it's not moby jump
它不是莫比奇妙跳
It is as if someone is going to wake it up, bite it
它是好像有人去叫醒它、咬它
It's time for a heartbeat
該心跳了
Then I'll... this is another earthquake in Taichung
那我就...這是另外一個台中的地震
3.7, as soon as the earthquake comes
3.7,地震一來開始
Bobo Bobo, the heartbeat is coming
波波波波,心跳就來了
it happened three times
曾經發生過三次
Although it's only three times, I'm super excited
雖然只有三次,我是超興奮
How come... Earthquakes are periodic
怎麼會有...地震是有周期性的
It's the whole world... I never mentioned it
這是全世界...我從來沒有提過
then i will make a metaphor
那我就做一個比喻
This is the normal heartbeat
這就是這個正常人心跳
Then there's a heart problem
然後就心臟有問題了
Start trimmer, start jumping wildly, don't jump at all
開始trimmer開始亂跳一跳都不跳
then jump again
然後又跳一下
Then sent to the hospital, of course the electric shock
然後送到醫院當然就電擊
He will jump up after the electric shock
電擊又啪啪啪啪他就會跳起來
So the earthquake Taichung machine in Hualien
所以那個花蓮的地震台中機
like electric shock
就好像電擊
So Yangmingshan may be broken
所以陽明山可能碎了
It's just that my heart hasn't jumped for a long time
就是心跳好久都沒跳
The earthquake shocked it and made him start jumping
地震把它電擊讓他開始跳
That's a metaphor
那這是比喻啦
not really the case
不是真的事情這樣
A fun thing is
一個好玩的事情就是
This heartbeat will kill
這個心跳會受命喔
The little mouse jumped hundreds of times
這動物小老鼠跳了幾百次
his life is short
他生命很短
Elephants are good at jumping very slowly
大象精於跳得很慢
then live longer
那就活得比較久
Of course that person is no longer an animal?
那人當然已經是不是動物了
People are no longer in this ordinary animal
人就已經不在這個一般動物
This quote means
這個引意就是說
Anyway, the faster the heartbeat, the shorter the life
反正心跳越快其實生命越短
Well if this extends it to volcanoes
那如果這個把它延伸到火山的話
those 18 minutes
那18分鐘
it's jumping super slow super slow
它是跳超慢超慢
So it can live for a long time
所以它可以活超久超久
I'm not scientific
我這是非科學啦
a bit silly
有點瞎掰了
ok then the last summary
好 那最後一個總結
Let's go back to Daping Mountain
我們又回到這個大平山跟
with this
跟這個
This vulgar position may
這個維俗位或者都會
Metropolis and Old Town of Taipei
台北都會跟古城
This Taipei city is a million people
這個台北都會是一個數百萬人
Of course the Vulgar position
那當然維俗位這個
Pompeii has 20,000 people
龐貝斯有兩萬人
This is much worse
這個差很多
That's about 10 kilometers away.
那距離其實都差不多10公里左右
are very similar distances
是非常類似的距離
that is volcanic
那以火山的
this big east volcano
這個大東火山
This date may be 6000 years
這個定年可能6000年吧
But the Vulgarian position was actually sprayed again in 1914
但是維俗位其實1914年又噴過一次
The heights of the Qixing Mountain and the Vulgar Seat are actually over 1,000.
那七星山跟維俗位的高度其實都1000出頭
That's mainly interesting
那主要有意思是這些
The area of our magma household is about 70 square kilometers
這個我們岩漿戶的面積大概70平方公里
Ordinary position about 400
維俗位大概400
In fact, it is 6 or 7 times larger
其實大了6、7倍
6 times is actually bigger
6倍 其實就比較大
Volcano is getting bigger
火山快點就大
It's shallower too
深度它也比較淺
So we go a little deeper
所以我們深度稍微深一點
but we are trying now
但是我們現在在努力
Find another 5 kilometers and 10 kilometers of magma chambers
再找5公里10公里的岩漿庫
This is what we have been doing for the last few years
這是我們最近這幾年的工作
Historical disasters, of course, this side is also very scary
歷史災害當然這個旁邊也是很可怕的
But Yangmingshan did not
但是陽明山沒有
The last one is what we want to convey today
最後這個是我們今天要傳達的重點
Whether it's a big volcano or a small volcano
不管它是大火山小火山
Population nearby or far away
人口在旁邊還是遠離
In fact, in the past, science can tell us
其實以前在科學可以告訴我們
You just have to do something very easy to monitor
你只要做監測非常容易的事情
There is probably a considerable degree of protection
大概就可以有相當程度的保障
That monitoring is scientifically speaking
那監測以科學來講
that is very simple
那是很簡單的事情
You just put the ruins down for some analysis and sorting.
你就是把遺跡擺下去做一些分析整理
and then probably give us some
然後大概就可以提供我們一些
good reference relic
很好的參考遺跡
The ancient city of Navisbowei is here
那維斯伯威古城在這邊
But Napoli so they keep doing it
但是Napoli所以他們還是繼續做
This is a volcanic city
這個都是屬於火山城市
cities on or around volcanoes
就是城市在火山的上面或周圍
That Taipei is also a volcano
那台北也是火山
one of the volcano cities
火山城市的一個
The question is, will the volcano move?
那問題就是說火山會不會動
we do not know
我們不知道
but we have to be prepared
但是我們要有準備
if one day it moves
如果哪一天它動的時候
we need to know in advance
我們要提前知道
That's the job of going to the Volcano Watch to fight
那就是到了火山觀正戰的工作
So a simple question
所以簡個簡單的問題
I am often asked by many people
也是常常好多人問我
So maybe now you guys can answer
所以可能現在你們可以回答了
Will the first one be active
第一個會不會在活動
Yes
會啊
I usually don't even think about it
我通常都不敢想會
i usually want to say
我通常都會想說
can not rule out
不能排除
more like this
比較有這個樣
Then the second is to say
然後第二個就是說
Spending money will be interesting
噴花錢會有意景吧
yes
會喔
everyone trust me
大家都相信我
I often go around giving speeches to people
我常常到處演講跟人家講
that's it
就是講這樣
But actually I'm pretty stressed when I go home
但其實我回家壓力蠻大
the day the volcano erupts
哪天火山噴發
I still haven't told everyone
我還是沒跟大家講
I might
我可能
Might have to kill myself like this
可能要自我了斷這樣
And where did the millions of citizens flee to?
然後這個幾百萬市民逃到哪去
This is the section chief of the exercise in Taipei
這個是台北市演習的那個科長
You keep checking on me, just asking what to do? What should Mr. Lin do?
一直來查我,就說怎麼辦?林老師怎麼辦?
He said where are our six million people going? I said don't scare yourself
他說我們六百萬人跑去哪裡?我說你不要嚇自己嘛
There is no such thing as six million people, right?
沒有六百萬人這種問題嘛對不對
Then Qiandu also wanted to say that we should move to Taichung.
那千督也很想說那我們就搬到台中去嘛
The last question has an answer
最後一個問題答案都有
We should not be in the ancient city next to us
我們應該不會是旁邊古城
Except for many natural conditions, the most important and the least
除了很多自然的條件最重要最少
Reality and space are different, there was no science two thousand years ago
實空不一樣,兩千年前沒有科學
people don't know what's going on
人民不知道發生什麼事情
but we now have science
但是我們現在有科學
Science can tell us many answers
科學可以告訴我們很多的答案
So the simple answer is no
所以答案很簡單就是不會
So it's festival
所以這是節儀啦
It means that we will live and die with the volcano.
就是要我們要跟火山一起共存亡
but through science
但是透過科學
Finally, I would like to thank the relevant units
最後就感謝相關的單位
Because this plan has actually been in the works for more than ten years.
因為這個計畫其實做了十幾年
It's this big plan that has been in the works for more than ten years.
就是這個大的計畫做了十幾年
not a single one
不是單一個這個
This department or Chinese can also pay for all this
這個部會或者中文也可以付的所有的這個
So we use various channels
所以我們就透過各種管道
Then go to persuade people to give money to people
然後去說服人家給地給錢給人
So let's build this bounce off the battle
所以我們來建構這個反彈關正戰
Okay, sorry for the delay.
好這個拖了一點點時間非常不好意思
thanks, thanks
謝謝 謝謝
Well we thank you researcher for a very good presentation
好我們謝謝您研究員非常精彩的演講
Now the rest of our time is open to questions
現在我們剩下的時間要開放給大家提問
We have prepared exquisite gifts on site
我們現場是有準備了精美的禮品
hand over here
在這邊手上
We have ten, so the first ten
我們有十份 所以頭十個人
If the first ten people ask questions, they will get a small gift
前面十個人提問的話會得到一份小小的贈品
There's that microphone in front of you guys
各位前面有那個麥克風
wait a minute please use the microphone if you want to ask a question
等一下如果要提問的話請你用麥克風
click that one
按一下那個有一個
green part
綠色的部位
This will turn the microphone on
這個就會把麥克風打開來
good
好
now please
現在請問
what's your problem
各位有什麼問題
good
好
here
這邊
Hello Mr. Lin
林老師好
good
好
Actually what I want to ask is
其實我要問的是
if a warning occurs say
如果發生預警說
There will be a big earthquake in the next ten days
接下來十天會有大地震
there will be a volcanic eruption
會有火山爆發
no results
結果沒有
seems more serious
好像比較嚴重
like a typhoon
就像颱風來了
put a fake result
放了假結果
No, my question is actually
沒有 我的問題其實是說
The characteristics of the Big Butt Volcano and other
大臀火山的特性跟其他的
other volcanoes
其他火山
For example, the volcanic nature of Hawaii
比方說夏威夷的火山特性
Is there any difference
有沒有不一樣
In other words, just ten days ago
也就是說剛剛的十天前
That dense vibration thing
那種密集的振波這件事情
Big Butt Volcano
事實上大臀火山
we have no way to prove
我們沒有辦法去證明
really like that
真的那樣子
Will time really explode in the future?
以後時間是不是真的爆發
unless it really explodes
除非它真的爆發
That experience comes from
那這個經驗是來自於
Hawaiian Volcanoes
夏威夷火山的情況
Will they be the same
那他們會不會是一樣
still may be different
還是有可能不同
Thanks
謝謝
this is a very good question
這個是非常好的問題
and you're an insider
而且你是內行人
the volcanic issue
這個火山議題
Actually not 100%
其實沒有百分之百
And every volcano behaves differently
而且每個火山的行為不一樣
In fact, the Hawaiian volcano and Mount Fuji
其實夏威夷火山跟富士山
Or that actually the volcano has very
或者那個其實火山有很
many kinds
很多種種類
Shrimp meat is also relatively viscous magma
蝦肉也是比較黏字性很高的岩漿
so it just won't explode
所以它就是不會炸
This one was blasted
這個用噴發炸的
It actually flows more like water
它其實會像比較像水就流
That's like this volcano in the Pacific Rim
那像環太平洋這個火山
it will explode like
它就會像炸開了
That's because of its viscosity
那原因是它的黏稠度
Or we say its acid-base scientifically
或者我們科學上說它的酸鹼
Its ratio of that SIO2
它的那個SIO2的比例
you can imagine that
你可以想像就是說
as a pot of water
當一個一鍋水
Shrimp meat is like a pot of water
蝦肉就像一鍋水
when you add it
你把它加的時候
the water will roll
那水會滾
But if you cook a pot of porridge
但是你如果是煮一鍋的稀飯
or corn chowder with words
或玉米濃湯的話
When the viscosity is high
那個黏稠度很高的時候
you boil boil boil it will
你煮煮煮它會
it will
它會
right
對不對
it's sticky
它那個很黏稠
it accumulates energy all the time
它會一直累積能量能量
then it's about to explode
然後它就要炸開來
so different volcanoes
所以不同的火山
In fact, its composition is different
其實它的成分不一樣
it behaves differently
它的行為不一樣
So we can't put shrimp flavor
所以我們不能把蝦味
or usually by fire
或者平常通過火
Any volcanic act takes
任何的火山的行為拿來
Predicting what will happen to our big volcanoes
預測我們大的火山會怎樣
In fact, to put it bluntly, everyone
其實說穿就是每個人
or everyone volcano
或者每個人火山
has its own unique personality
都有它的獨特的個性
We want to predict the behavior of a person
我們要預測一個人的行為
We can't put A's person's
我們不能把A的人的
past to predict B's
過去的去預測B的
In fact, the risk is great
其實這個風險很大
We better do it for A
我們最好就是針對A做
good observation
很好的觀測了解
See how his behavior tends to be
看他的行為傾向是怎樣
Then we make predictions based on the strategy
然後我們根據戰略去做預測
But even then we can't
但是即使這樣我們也不可能
In fact, there are several volcanoes that say
其實有好幾個火山都說
I thought it would erupt, but it didn't
認為會噴發結果沒有
this is
這個是
Sometimes for a very simple reason
有時候因為很簡單的道理嘛
Your magma keeps moving up and down
你那個岩漿一直抬抬抬
Successors are unreasonable. In fact, Mount Fuji used to be
後繼無理其實富士山就曾經
this 2001
這個2001年
Japanese scientists and the government
日本的科學家他跟政府
is nervous as hell
是緊張的要命
Why do they earthquake from 20 km
為什麼他們地震從20公里
I have been running and running for 2 kilometers
一直跑跑跑拉了2公里
He thought it might come up tomorrow or the day after tomorrow
他以為可能明後天就上來
be quiet from now on
就從此就安安靜靜
So it's still his
所以這還是有他的
this uncertainty
這個不確定性
We can only do it by looking at the skills
我們只能看技能力去做
yes
是
It is the shadow of the S wave and the phantom of the P wave that you mentioned earlier
就是你前面提到的S波的陰影還有P波的煙幻
These are the two phenomena of smoke and phantom arrival
就是煙幻到達的這兩種現象
Then these two phenomena are what I just said from the teacher.
那這兩種現象就是我從老師剛才講的
I think all I know is that it reflects that it is a representative book
我覺得我能知道就是它能反映出它是代表書
There is a liquid substance in the ground
地底下有液態物質的存在
How can we infer from the existence of this liquid substance?
那從這液態物質的存在我們怎麼去推估
It is possible to estimate the volume of the magma chamber and its depth
它是可以去推估出這岩漿庫的體積以及它的深度
Is this information? Thanks
這些資訊嗎?謝謝
The volume is based on the presence or absence of side stations on our surface
體積我們就是根據我們地表的側站的有跟沒有
We can roughly outline a range
我們大概就可以勾勒化一個範圍
that depth is a good question
那深度是一個好問題
Depth because of more scientific issues
深度因為比較科學性的問題
That is to say, I didn't talk much here.
就是說我在這邊沒有很講
That is to say, I use earthquakes at different depths for cross-comparison
就是說我用不同的深度的地震去做交叉比對
There is a little bit of this depth past and this depth
就是有一點這個深度過去的跟這個深度
If cut to yes or no
如果切到有跟沒有
It has an angle, right?
它就有個夾角對不對
If at the very surface it doesn't have both
如果在很地表的時候它兩個都沒有
because it is kilometers
因為它是公里的
start to have a little gap
就開始有一點差距
So take it slow
所以慢慢的去推估
Of course this is just an estimate
當然這個只是出估
That's why we have our second big plan.
所以我們才有第二個大的計畫
Hope to make more accurate
希望把更精準的做出來
So something like this
所以大概是這樣的
At present, the preliminary results can only reach this
目前初步結果只能到這樣
yes
是
because probably the whole world
因為大概全世界
I think I'm the first to do this
我認為我第一個這樣做的
Because like Mount Fuji
因為比如像富士山
Actually theirs or Hasber Mountain
其實他們那個或者哈斯伯伯山
they are very clear
他們都很清楚的
What's in store along the river
沿江庫什麼
the evidence is very clear
證據非常清楚
people don't need to do this
人家不需要這樣做
That's because it's too controversial in Taiwan
那因為在台灣就爭議性太大
We can't see that thing on the surface
我們地表上看不到那個東西
That's why I worked so hard to come up with this way.
所以才千辛萬苦的想出這個辦法去
to verify
去驗證
so this is
所以這個是
should be the only
應該是唯一
I know so far
我目前知道
The only person in science who does this
科學上唯一有人這樣做的
yes
是
Hello Mr. Lin
林老師你好
I want to ask is in the past geological records
我想問就是在過往的地質紀錄中
Is there any record of volcanic debris in the Datong volcanic group like Unzen Volcano?
大同火山群有沒有像雲仙火山這種自災性程度的火山碎屑的紀錄嗎
In the history of our mankind, there is no
歷史上面我們人類歷史上沒有
But in geology
但是在地質界
If there is information, I can show you that debris road.
如果有信息我可以帶你看那個碎屑的路頭
what's that called
在那個叫什麼
The kind with debris in several places
好幾個地方有碎屑的那種
that kind of road
那種路頭
We haven't decided on the land and year yet.
那地年這一塊我們還沒有定
We are now just like six thousand years is just a year of volcanic ash
我們現在只是像六千年只是定一個火山灰的地年
The land on the other side of the debris has not yet been overcome
那碎屑那邊的地年這一塊還沒有克服
But at least there's evidence out there
但至少是有證據在外頭
is visible from the surface
就是在地表看得到
yes
是
So it is not sure whether it is possible to be as serious as Japan's self-disaster
所以還不確定是有可能像日本那種自災性這麼嚴重的嗎
Are you sure you know there is such a record?
是還沒有確定知道有這個紀錄嗎
have this record
有這個紀錄
But our human history is
但是我們人類的歷史就是
In Taiwan only
在台灣只有
No more than 1000 years or so without these records
沒比1000年或多就沒有這些紀錄
ok thank you teacher
好 謝謝老師
Hello teacher
老師好
Chase Volcanic Group
那個大通火山群
Because it is quite old
因為它的年代也算滿久的
More than 28 million to 200,000
2800多萬到20萬
Recently, it was just about 50 million
最近是剛剛講的是5000萬左右
5000 years
5000年
So a magma in this place
所以這個地方的一個岩漿
Distribution of double libraries
雙庫的分布
Historically
以歷史來看
Should it be concentrated
應該是不是集中的
because when it's about to spray flowers
因為它要噴花的時候
There must be cracks sucked out
必須要有裂吸出來
right
對
at Big Butt Volcano in this
在大臀火山在這個
triangle fault this period
三角斷層這個時期
There may also be cracks and suction that will spray out
還有可能有裂吸會噴出來
But the volume of the magma chamber
可是岩漿庫的體積
Correspondingly, it must also be sucked with crack
相對的也必須要跟裂吸
have a match
要有一個搭配
So when it comes to spraying flowers
所以說要說到噴花
Is there one of these two
是不是這兩個有一個
there is a proof
有一個印證性的東西
Yes, many academic circles or our experts probably think that it means
是 是現在很多學界或者我們專家大概認為就是說
The current triangular fault
目前的這個三角斷層
In fact, it is a bad department
其實它就是一個劣系嘛
The magma is likely to be on this inferior system
那岩漿很可能就是在這個劣系上面
this climb up
這個爬上來
It is along this line of development
就是沿這個發育上來
the future is actually
那未來其實
We can't be sure
我們也不敢篤定啦
But the possibility is possible
但是這種可能性是有可能的
So this goes up this direction of the triangle fault
所以這沿著三角斷層的這個走向上面
Is Qiqisan right next to the fault at the foot of the mountain?
七七三就在三角斷層的旁邊嘛
The big oil pit is not far away
那大油坑也離不遠嘛
Then we saw the verification activity
那我們看見那個維證的活動
That is, the seismic activity is all on the side of the Seven Seventh Three Oil Pit.
就是地震活動都在七七三大油坑這邊
It seems to match the geometry of the triangle fault.
跟三角斷層的那個幾何看起來還蠻吻合的
Therefore, it is very likely that the inferior system along the fault zone of the Triangular Fault
所以是很有可能沿著三角斷層這個斷層帶的劣系
lava will come up
岩漿會上來
This is guesswork
這是推估啦
Another inference is that
還有一個推理就是說
Because the triangular fault is a kind of fault before the earthquake
因為三角斷層它是屬於一種震斷前的一個
only then will there be contact
才會有聯繫
years to now
多年來到現在
200,000 years to the last 50 million years
二十萬年到最近幾年的五千萬年
Because this time comes in the crust
因為這時間在地殼來
in terms of address
地址的來講
is it going to stabilize
它是不是去穩定
or there will be signs of activity
或是會有在活動的跡象
Is there any research on this
這方面有沒有研究說
There is a comparison problem with the magma chamber
跟岩漿庫有一個比對的問題
Because if the magma chamber is on the other side
因為岩漿庫假如在那一頭
over here over here
這邊在這一頭
It is also impossible to have the problem of spraying flowers
也不可能有噴花的問題
This is actually a good question
這個其實是一個好問題
because of how we do research now
因為我們現在怎麼做的研究
to citizen is now
到公民就是現在
you have to compare with the past
你要跟過去比
to know that it is regional stability
才知道它是區域穩定
still unstable
還是區域不穩定
But past evidence actually
但是過去的證據其實
super blurry
超模糊的
So we just can't compare
所以我們就是無從比較
so many people say
所以有很多人講說
Magma is in the process of cooling
岩漿是在冷卻的過程
Then of course nothing will happen in the future
那當然以後就沒有什麼事情
still not cooling
還是都不是在冷卻
Evidence
證聞
good evidence to control his activities now is up and down
好的證據去控制他現在是往上還往下的活動
yes yes yes of course
是是是那當然
Yes Yes Yes
是是是
There is still a lot of work to do after all this
這個都後戲還有很多工作還真的要繼續做
Thanks
謝謝
Hello Professor Lin
林教授您好
two questions
兩個問題請教
The first one is like our landslides
第一個就是說像我們土石流
When we all have to issue alerts
我們都要發布警戒的時候
Just say how much rainfall exceeds the yellow alert
就說雨量超過多少黃色警戒
Or the amount of rainfall exceeds the red alert
或者雨量超過多少紅色警戒
I don't know if our TVO has any data now
那不曉得我們的TVO現在有沒有什麼數據
when the earthquake exceeds how much
當地震超過多少
or how much the ground temperature exceeds
或者地溫超過多少
or when the concentration of carbon dioxide reaches
或是二氧化碳濃度到多少的時候
we're going to publish the next
我們要發布緊接
we live right under the volcanic triangle
我們就住在火山三角下
we care about this stack
我們關心這一疊
Then the second question is
那另外第二個問題就是
small oil pit it
小油坑它
We now call it a blowout word
我們現在稱它叫爆裂口的話
that it didn't stand to burst
那它沒有站在爆裂
we call it a blowout port better
我們稱它爆裂口比較好
It would be more appropriate to call it the landslide
還是稱它叫崩塌地會比較恰當
Now the second question should be the blowout
現在第二個問題應該是爆裂口
because of the collapse
因為崩塌
Collapsed
崩塌其實
because most think it's a burst
因為大部分都覺得它是一個爆裂
a rupture in a fault zone
斷裂帶的一個爆裂口
That collapse behavior is not like that
那崩塌的行為不是像那樣
collapse is just a sag
崩塌只是下陷
but it is a concave whole
但它是一個凹的整個
like a pit
像一個坑那樣
So it's not the same as collapsing
所以跟塌陷不太一樣
it's a blast
它是一個爆
and we have a lot of steam
而且我們有很多蒸氣
what is this jet
這個噴氣什麼
the first question is
那第一個問題是
next to
緊接
this is very difficult
這個非常的難
but
但是
One NCDR is the center of the international battlefield
一個NCDR就是國際戰場中心
Or the Executive Yuan or the Ministry of the Interior
或者行政院什麼什麼內政部
Forced me to talk about this every day
每天就逼著我要講這件事情
But I'm here to be honest
但是我在這裡老實講就是說
Actually, I know very little
其實我知道也很有限
But the people or the government need a standard
但是民眾或政府就需要一個標準
So we're forced to set a standard
所以我們被逼著就設一個標準
we try very
我們試著很
because there is no history
因為沒有歷史
no background
沒有背景
so we don't know
所以我們不知道
How big is this volcano
這個火山到什麼程度才會
Only then will the dam collapse
才會崩壩
if it has previous records
如果它有前面的紀錄
we can probably use it as a reference
我們大概就可以做參考
But we don't have this record
但是這個我們就沒有這個紀錄
So we can only put
所以我們只能把
compulsively put other volcanic
強迫性的把其他的火山的
Many volcanoes in Japan are used as a reference
日本的很多火山拿來做一個參考
But I must say that this reference is actually
但是我必須說這個參考其實
really just for reference
真的僅做參考
cannot
不能
Much of this is still unknown
這個這個好多還是未知
difficult things
很難的事情
Because many people are in this civil government
因為好多人都這個民間政府
Most have been asking about this
大部分都一直在問這件事情
This is with effort
這個有帶努力
ok lady
好 這位女士
Teacher Lin, I want to ask you
林老師我想請教你
Because I often take Chinese and foreign tourists to small tourists
因為我常常帶中外遊客去小遊客
I remember about half a year ago
那我記得大概半年前
There was a magnitude 5.5 earthquake this year
今年有一次5.5級的地震
very close to taipei
很靠近台北
After a few days, I will take tourists to Xiaoyoukeng
那過幾天以後我帶遊客到小遊坑
I just realized I haven't gone yet
我就發現我還沒走到
as soon as i got out of the parking lot i heard
我一下停車場我就聽到
Loud sound like pit shooting an airplane
像坑射飛機的很大的聲音
i never heard
我從來沒有聽過
then you're the first to hear
那你是第一個人聽到
I always
我一直
the airport is very big
飛機場非常大
Because I often take Chinese and foreign tourists to that scenic spot
因為我常常帶中外遊客到那個景點去
I've never heard of such a big
我從來沒有聽過這麼大的
As big as a crater plane right next to your ear
像坑射飛機就在你耳朵旁邊這麼大
I was thinking then
我那時候就在想說
My video should start leading everyone away
我視頻應該開始帶著大家逃
escape with everyone
帶著大家逃
But two months later
可是後來再過兩個月
when i go
我在去的時候
that voice is gone
那個聲音就不見
Then you often monitor over there
那你常常在那邊監測
i don't know
我不知道說
This is a very common phenomenon
這種是很常見的現象
it's just that loud
就是會有這麼大的聲音
The sound of your jet is different from the ones I usually go to
你那個噴氣口的聲音跟往常我去的不一樣
The other one is that the information I read is that
那另外一個是我讀到的資料是說
Two judgments whether it is a volcano
兩個判斷是不是火火山
one that you just listed
一個是你剛剛有列出來
What I've read always says 200,000 years
我讀到的資料一直是說20萬年
The first condition is 200,000 years
第一個條件是20萬年
The second condition is whether there is a magma chamber
第二個條件是有沒有岩漿庫
Then I know that we now know that there are magma chambers.
那我知道說岩漿庫我們現在知道是有的
Said that we used to define it as repairing volcanoes or even stone volcanoes
說我們以前定義成修火山或甚至於石火山
Then I also read about Guishan Island
那我也讀到龜山島
The last eruption appears to have been 200,000 years ago
最後一次噴發好像是20萬年前的事
four times
有四次
Then I want to know the dating method that says I am more correct
那我想知道說我比較正確的定年法
i should say
我應該講
which one should be used
應該用哪一個
which was the last eruption
最後一次噴發是哪一個
Because I obviously 200,000 is not the same
因為我顯然20萬是不一樣
200,000 is not
20萬不是
ten thousand years
就是一萬年
10,000 years is actually related to the Central Geological Survey
一萬年其實跟中央那個地質調查所
active fault
他們用活動斷層
That is, the most active active fault is 10,000 years old.
就是最活躍的活動斷層就是一萬年
So ten thousand years is them
所以一萬年就是他們
In the geological world, they are equivalent to having a
就是地質界他們等於是有一個
as long as it is a living geology
只要是活的地質
Regardless of volcanic faults, all are references
不管火山斷層都是以萬作參考
Two hundred thousand is too long
二十萬太久了
The two hundred thousand...
二十萬那個...
And you just heard that I really hope
然後你剛剛聽到我真的很希望
if you can take your time
你如果能把你的時間
probably tell me
大概跟我講
Because we now have a 24 hour record
因為我們現在有24小時紀錄
Then if you probably have the truth
那你如果大概有其實
how often do you say
你說有多頻繁
In my impression, I watched it carefully for half a year
我印象中我仔細的看了半年
i spent a lot of time
我花了滿多時間
20 hour inspection
就是20小時檢查
About 10 days on average
平均大概10天
two weeks
兩個禮拜
Anyway, about 10 days or so
反正就是大概10天上下
I can probably argue
我大概就可以爭論到
There is the sound of this so-called place name
有這種所謂地名的聲音
But sometimes very often
但是有時候會非常頻繁
Sometimes it's 3 days
有時候就是聯繫3天
always have
一直都有
that sometimes happens sporadically
那有時候就會偶發性的
Just once or twice a week
就是一個禮拜就一兩聲
Dirty, right?
很髒對不對
so if you can really hear
所以你如果真的聽得到
Because I often ask people
因為我常常問人家說
Because of my information, I saw that it really exists.
因為我資料我看到真的有嘛
but i didn't really hear anyone
但是我沒有真正有人聽到過
So you probably have this very precious
所以你大概這個是蠻珍貴的
is that I believe he usually looks like
就是我相信他平常看起來就是
just pissed off
就是就是冒氣了
But occasionally found that there will be something like
但是偶發現了會有像
like firecrackers
像像鞭炮那樣的
loud this
很大聲的這個
popping sound
啪 炸開來聲音
Otherwise, you will not receive my earthquake
否則我那地震你收不到
yes yes that should be
是是那應該就是
because what you describe is
因為你描述的就是
it is relatively low frequency
它是比較低頻的
a little longer
比較長一點的時間
right right right right
對對對對對對
wow this is real
哇 這個很真
yes
是
if the volcano
如果火火山的話
fire volcano it can come in fire volcano
火火山它可以進來火火山
can there be a way
能不能有個方法
can it be made into a stone volcano
能不能讓它成為石火山
right
是吧
because it's on a volcano
因為它在火火山
while it's working
它在運作的時候
we invest something in
我們投資一些東西進去
Yes or no
是不是
then to destroy it
然後來破壞它
volcanic stuff
火火山的東西
This, this, this is a bit difficult
這個這個這個有點難
This is like an earthquake. Some people say that the energy of Zhentan is lost.
這個就像地震有些人說震潭能量失放
So this fault
所以這個斷層嘛
He just wanted to say we just let it make a small earthquake
他就想說我們就讓它小地震
A big earthquake turns into many small earthquakes
大地震變成很多小地震
we water it
我們把它灌水
This is a scientific quake
這個是科學式震
Fault you pump water into it
就斷層你把它打水進去
it will start to slip
它就會開始滑
release energy
就釋放能量
But this is very risky
但是這個非常風險很大
no one dares to do this why
沒有人敢這樣做為什麼
How to do it?
怎麼做?
Yes, yes, it is fine normally
對對對平常它反而沒事
you add water to it
你把它加水
That's it, a big earthquake, who is responsible
就是它來一個大地震誰負責
This is actually
這個其實
You can't control whether it will increase or decrease
你沒辦法控制它的要加還是要減
The same problem is that the volcano
同樣的問題就是說火山
the natural world i think we
那個大自然界我覺得我們
probably difficult
大概很難吧
With current technology it is possible
在目前的科技上面可能
is it possible
有沒有可能
how to do this
這怎麼要做啊
if i stand over there
這如果我站在那邊
how could he want to go
他怎麼會想去
He works or stands there
他工作還是站在那邊
Because the magma chamber is over there.
因為岩漿庫就在那邊啊
Yes Yes Yes
是是是
it would have been a big thing
它本來是一個很大的東西
We can slowly reduce it
我們可以慢慢來把它減小
replace it with this
把它換成這個
If the line is like this, that's right.
動線這樣的話就對了
It should be possible
應該是說有可能
But now I don't know what to do
但是現在不曉得怎麼做
yes
是
Okay, Professor Lin, ask for advice.
好 那個林教授請教一下
That is to say you just mentioned
就是說您剛剛有提到
Huangchi Park is a huge volcano
黃池公園是一個超大的火山
so-called extra-large or medium-sized
那所謂的超大或是中型
or how a small volcano is defined
或是小型火山是怎麼定義
So how dangerous is it?
那它的危害程度大概是怎麼樣
Probably we can now easily define
大概我們現在很容易界定
just look at it
就是看它岩漿戶
Like this volume of the magma house
像岩漿戶的這個體積
It seems like the one in Huangchi Park
像黃池公園那個好像大概
Seems like thousands of cubic kilometers
好像是幾千個立方公里
A few thousand, I don't know if fifteen thousand or how much
幾千喔 不知道一千五還是多少
That's just like ours
那剛剛像我們那個其實
The big round volcano may only be
大輪火山那個可能只有
Only a hundred
只有百而已啦
About 100 programs
大概百所有的程序
Of course it's the magma house
那當然就岩漿戶
The bigger the magma chamber, it only needs to be squeezed out a little bit, which is actually quite impressive
岩漿庫越大,它只要擠出一點點,其實就很可觀
If the magma chamber is small, of course it is less dangerous
那岩漿庫如果小的話,它當然就危險就很小
So volcanoes are graded
所以火山他們有分級啦
According to the magma, it is divided into 12345 levels
那根據那個岩漿的那個分了12345級
graded
有分級的
Just now I saw a few after the volcanic eruption
剛剛前面有看到幾個是火山噴發之後
There is an example of escaping
那這邊有逃離的例子
Then I want to ask that after the volcano ceases to be active
那我想問那火山停止活動之後
How soon can they go back and live there
他們多久才可以回去那邊生活
wow this is another problem
哇,這個又是一個難題
In fact, it is relatively easy for people to evacuate from the volcano
其實火山叫民眾撤離,相對的比較容易
And after the evacuation, when will they be allowed to go back
然後一撤離以後,哪時候能讓人家回去
People in general always want to go back
一般民眾都一直想回去
Looks like as long as it doesn't smoke, he wants to go back
看起來就只要不冒煙,他就想回去
But the role unit, the government is actually very difficult
可是角色單位,政府其實非常難
Because what I just talked about is when the magma goes up
因為就剛剛講的是岩漿往上竄的時候
We can easily see those
我們很容易看得到那些
But he stringed to a certain word
但是他串串串到某個字
Then it started when there was no change
然後就開始就是沒有再變化的時候
When will it suddenly come together again?
哪時候會再突然又再串起來
that the evidence starts to get murky.
即那個證據就開始很模糊
even say when it will start to be quiet
甚至說哪時候會開始安靜
This is not a good reference standard
這個沒有很好的參考標準
Sometimes it is one of the decision-making units
有時候就是決製單位的一個
it's just a decision
就是一個決定而已
So going back is actually a big trouble
所以回去其實是一個很大的麻煩
when can we go back
就是哪時候可以回去
like hawaii, right?
就像夏威夷對不對
move at midnight
午夜的時候動動動
then it seems to stop
然後就好像停了
recently again
最近又來
like that paris island
像那個巴黎島也是一樣
Last October was like two months of activity
去年10月就好像有兩個月活動
Then it stops in the middle
然後這個中間就停了
That July the last July
那7月最近7月
Paris Island is back in action
巴黎島又開始活動起來
So when he first moved
所以他當一開始動的時候
That kind of estimation is actually more difficult.
那種預估其實就比較難
But from being quiet to moving
但是從安靜變成要動
It's actually easier
其實是比較容易
from hole to silence
從洞要變成安靜
that is
也就是
not so easy
不是那麼容易
so still
所以還是
want a lot
要很多
lady behind
小姐在後面
i want to ask
我想請問一下
That researcher Lin is
那個林研究員就是
Because I told you a long time ago
因為之前很久以前我講過說
Earthquakes can be predicted with animals
地震可以用動物來預測
like a fish or a snake or something
就是好比魚或蛇或什麼
But have you ever thought about using animals to
但是你有沒有想過就是用動物來
conduct
進行
i don't know maybe you're not very practical either
我不知道這可能你也不太實際
but maybe there is a way
但或許是個方法
Have you ever been through this period?
你有經歷過這一段嗎
still have you thought about it
還是你有想過
this is not bad
這個不錯
Why do we use animals for earthquakes
地震為什麼我們要用動物
in what strange way
用什麼奇奇怪的方法
Because the science of earthquake prediction
因為以地震預測科學
upper level of science
上面科學的層面
Everyone thinks it's not feasible
大家覺得還沒有可行
so everyone is
所以大家就是
If you go to Western medicine
你如果去找西醫
I found out that you are terminally ill and cannot be cured.
發現說你這個是絕症不能救
Then everyone is looking for a way
然後大家就是找偏方
But in terms of volcanoes
但是以火山的話
He talks to you about the science chapter
他就科學章跟你講說
There is a lot of evidence that volcanoes cost money to erupt
火山要噴花錢就有很多證據的
Why should I look for a remedy?
我幹嘛去找偏方呢
So in terms of volcanoes
所以以火山的話
You do these monitoring for formal evidence
你就正規證據的做這些監測
probably the answer
大概就可以達到答案的
But the earthquake is still touching
但是地震就是還在摸手
So the idea of thousands or hundreds of dollars will come out
所以就千幾百塊的想法就會出來
Thanks
謝謝
I want to confirm one thing with your professor
我想向您教授確認一件事情
A few months ago in Beitou there was an earthquake at more than four o'clock
幾個月前在北投有一個四點多的地震
Exactly the same result when I saw
正一樣結果我看的時候
It seems to be near Zhongshan Building
是好像在中山樓附近
It's very close to the Tatun Volcanic Group
那離那個大屯火山群很近
Later, the Meteorological Bureau said that it was due to the movement of the plate.
後來氣象局說是那個板塊移動的關係
but i doubt it
但是我覺得很懷疑
so according to your opinion
所以根據您的意見
The earthquake caused by the same thing
那一次的正一樣所引起的地震
Is it really a plate movement?
到底是真的是板塊移動呢
It is also a post-increase of the volcanic group
還是火山群的一個增後
if i remember correctly
我如果沒記錯
you may be asking to have a
你可能是問有一個
They called it the Beitou Earthquake at first
他們一開始說叫北投地震
right
對
This scale is 5.7
這規模5.7
because for many years
因為很多年來
There is no earthquake that happened in the center of Taipei City
台北市沒有正央發生過的地震
The earthquake was actually
那個地震其實是
The weather should be right.
氣象裡講的應該是沒錯
The reason is that the earthquake was deep
原因是那個地震很深
more than 100 kilometers
100多公里
So that is related to our Philippine Sea plate
所以那個是跟我們菲律賓海板塊
go north in silence
往北隱默在
Earthquakes in this hidden belt
這個隱默帶的板塊的地震
It's not in this 10km of the volcano
它不是在火山的這個10公里
this shallow surface
這個很淺的地表
If it is within 5 km 10 km
如果它是在5公里10公里
That's more to do with volcanoes
那就是跟火山比較有關係
but is it 140 or what
但是它是140還是多少
140 kilometers
140公里
that's deep
那是很深
It is related to the plate
是跟板塊有關係
So the Meteorological Bureau's interpretation is
所以氣象局這種解釋是
basically ok
基本上是OK的
It is scientifically accepted
就是科學上面是接受的
right
對
sir behind
先生在後面
Hello Mr. Lin
林老師您好
What We Know About the Threat of Volcanoes in Northern Taiwan
我們所知道在台灣北部的火山的威脅
In addition to the big hip volcano
除了大臀火山之外
haiti volcano in geelung it is also a volcano of fire
在基隆的海地火山它也是火火山
And it may have been active in Keelung Sea School in 1867
而且它可能在1867年的基隆大海校是有活動的
Will we address such disaster risks in the future?
那未來我們會不會針對這樣的災害風險
will do some scientific research
會做一些科學上的研究
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, I'm personally very interested
會 我個人就非常有興趣
You are actually many, many professional
你其實就很多很多專業的
Because there is a seabed and a volcano directly below Keelung Port.
因為基隆港那個正下方就有個海底就有個火山
submarine volcano
海底火山
And they went to explore the ocean
而且他們去做海洋的探證
That volcanic sea will be very steamy
那個火山海會很冒氣
It means it's a volcano
代表那是火火山
The teacher Xi Jinping from CUHK and the teacher from Yangshan National Taiwan University
那個中大的習近平老師還有那個台大洋山的老師
they just do some research
他們就做一些調查
Then I also believe
然後我也很相信
I personally believe this to be proven
我個人很相信這個要證實
It was the sea school in 1867
就是1867年那一次的海校
It is probably because it was said in the early days that the sea school caused by the earthquake
很可能是因為早期都說地震造成的海校
But the volcanic, submarine volcanic activity caused the sea school
但是火山 海底火山活動造成的海校
In fact, the possibility is quite high
其實可能性蠻高的
but need evidence
但是需要證據
that we need to investigate
就是我們需要做調查
So the future government will also do this
所以這一塊未來政府也去做
I personally will be very involved in doing it
我個人也會很投入去做
It's just that the investigation and research in the sea is more difficult
只是在海裡的調查研究比較難
So we need more of these technologies
所以我們需要更多的這些技術
or some way to overcome
或者一些方法才能克服
but that's worth doing
不過那很值得做的東西
yes
是
Literary performance
文演
Hello teacher
老師好
two questions
兩個問題
The first question is about the prediction of volcanic eruptions
第一個問題是關於火山爆發的預測
It's what you just mentioned
就是你剛剛有提到就是說
If you try to predict a volcanic eruption
如果盡量預測火山爆發的話
We can see that it was before the earthquake
我們可以看就是地震的生前
It is possible to slowly change forward from a relatively deep place
就是可能從比較深的地方慢慢變前
Then but what I want to ask is
然後但是我想要問的是
The speed at which the magma is extruded from the ground
這個岩漿從地底擠出來的這個速度
how fast it can
它能夠多快
Like if a whole bunch of omens happened within two hours today
像是如果今天一大堆預兆都在兩個小時之內發生
Like some hot spring water getting hot
像是什麼溫泉水變燙啊
or place names
或者是地名之類的
just too helpless
就是太沒有辦法
could it be in two hours
它有沒有可能是在兩個小時
maybe or a
可能或是一個
Within this hour, all earthquake-prone people will be
在這個小時之內就會全部頻繁地震地民
Then the water temperature of the hot springs and the like
然後溫泉的水溫奏生之類
Is it possible to have such a fast speed
就是有沒有可能有這麼快的速度
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
Excuse me
不好意思
And then the second question is about the crater lake
然後第二個問題是有關於那個火口湖
It's what I read in a magazine
就是我之前在雜誌上讀到就是
There are three three crater lakes in Africa
非洲有三座三個火口湖
Then what used to happen was
然後曾經發生過的事情是
It's the volcano under the crater lake.
就是那個火口湖下方的火山
gas eruption
就是氣體噴發
which then creates carbon dioxide in the lake
然後造成湖泊裡面的二氧化碳
concentration saturation etc.
濃度飽和之類的
And then this carbon dioxide floats out of this lake
然後這個二氧化碳就飄出了這個湖泊
and killed an entire village in one night
然後在一個晚上之內就殺死了整個村莊的人
Then what I want to ask is
那我想要請問就是
Is it possible for this to happen in Taiwan?
台灣有可能發生這種事情嗎
because we just heard
因為我們剛剛有聽到
That is, Taiwan has Haitian volcanoes.
就是台灣是有海地火山的
There are many hot springs
還有很多溫泉
I have no idea
我不知道
Is it because Taiwan has this condition that this kind of thing will happen?
就是台灣有這個條件會發生這種事情嗎
that's it thank you
就這樣 謝謝
Yes Yes
是 是
The first question is to say
第一個問題就是說
because one hour two hours
因為一個小時 兩個小時
Suddenly the volcano erupts
突然就火山噴發
basically it should be hard
基本上應該是很難
Because the magma is actually very viscous when it moves.
因為岩漿其實它的台身移動其實是很粘稠
It will not run from 5km to 10km to the surface like a bomb
它不會像炸彈一樣一下從5公里10公里就跑到地表
can't be that fast
不可能那麼快速
Usually weeks or months
通常都是幾個禮拜或者幾個月
even for several years
甚至有到幾年都有
it's running slowly
它就慢慢地竄慢慢地竄
So within a short period of time, probably within a day
所以那個很短時間一天以內大概
It should be from the school ceremony, but there is no
應該是從學禮上面是沒有
about crater lake
那有關火口湖
In fact, because it is full of your volcano
其實那個因為是滿點你的火山
there is a crater
就是有火山口
like a lake
就好像一個湖泊
Then it will rain and a lot of water will accumulate
然後就會下雨就積很多的水
That volcanic gas is actually a lot of acid
那火山氣體其實很多有流酸
And CO2 is the most
還有CO2是最多
There is also a lot of acid
流酸也滿多的
So these can easily become sour
所以這些很容易就會變成酸
Carbonic acid, fluidic acid, etc.
碳酸、流酸這些
Of course, the same is true for plant organisms or animals.
那當然對植物生物或者動物其實也是
quite a big impact
影響蠻大的
so you just have to be in crater lake
所以你只要在火山口湖
if there is volcanic activity
如果真的有火山活動的話
In fact, the water will become very acidic.
那其實那個水都會變得很酸
will affect
會造影響
But under the sea
但是在海底下的話
This problem may be less
這個問題可能就比較小
Because the sea is water after all, it is big
因為海畢竟是水是很大的
so it gets diluted
所以它會被稀釋掉
But the lake has very little water
但是湖的話水量很少
So it will be relatively high concentration
所以它就會比較濃度很高
will be more harmful
才會比較傷害
The sea is probably unless it happens to be in a submarine crater
那海大概除非是剛好在海底火山口的
Creatures there may be affected
那裡的生物可能會受影響
But it's easy to dilute
不過還是很容易稀釋掉的
yes
是
There's another one here
這邊還有一位
Hello teacher
老師好
What about Chase Volcano?
請問大通火山呢
Our date according to the Volcano Society is
我們這根據火山會的定年是
The last climb was within a few thousand years
最後一次攀發在幾千年以內
then ask the teacher
那請問老師
The date of the volcanic meeting is
火山會的定年是
probably what kind of method
大概要是什麼樣的方法
may the teacher explain
可以請老師解釋一下嗎
volcano will it actually be
火山會它其實就
Simple, they all use a lot
簡單他們都很多就用
carbon fourteen its some half-life
碳十四它的一些半衰期
So many address circles use half-life
所以很多地址界都是用半衰期
then it is a decay how many years it takes
那它就是一個衰減它需要多少年
Then see that the ratio has decayed several times
然後看到是比例是衰減了幾次
then how many years
然後就是多少年
It's probably like this for many years
很多地年大概都是這樣
Just use the half-life of the earth year
就是用那個半衰期的地年
The half-life of course
那半衰期當然有
Carbon fourteen is often used for thousands of years to ten thousand years
碳十四是比較幾千年到萬年常常被用的
But if it's hundreds of thousands of years or millions
但是如果是幾十萬年或百萬
It has additionally this radiological accreditation
它有另外的這個放射驗譽
That can already be made dumb or dumb or something like that
那也已經可以做做啞啞或啞啞之類的
So they have professionals who are doing this
所以他們有專業有人在做這一塊的
Yes Yes Yes
是是是
Is it okay, here is the last one
有沒有好這邊有最後一位
last question
最後一個問題
yes
是
I just want to ask
就是我想請問一下
Can the volcanic crushed crab flow predict the direction?
那個火山碎蟹流可不可以預知方向
Because at that time Pompeii would be
因為那時候龐貝古城會被
will be submerged by the volcanic shardcrab flow
會被火山碎蟹流淹沒
That is, it goes in that direction
也就是它從那個方向過去
In addition, there is another Napoleon director's place
另外還有另外的拿波理事的地方
If it's distributed at the Datong event in Taipei
那如果像是台北大同活動分發的話
Can we just predict which direction it's going?
我們可不可以就是預知它往哪個方向
Then we can avoid that disaster
然後我們可以避免掉那個災害
yes the answer is yes
是 答案是可以的
It's as simple as water
很簡單就是就跟水一樣
you pour the water down
你把水一潑下去
it goes to the lowest flow
它就是往那個最低的流
that's actually for this
那其實為了這個
In fact, Japan, especially Japan, has done a lot of work
其實像日本特別日本做了很多工作
It looks at the village for example
它譬如說看那個村莊
That, that, that ancient underground is a village
那個那個那個古地下来就是村莊
then what do they do
然後他們怎麼辦
That that water spilled into the sea and rushed to the village
那個那個水泄流下海就沖到村莊
they do something like this
他們就做類似這個
gutter or retaining wall
排水溝或者擋土牆
It's a bit like the concept of flood control
就是有點像防洪那個概念
Just be a very, very resolute body
就是做一個很很很堅毅的體那樣
When the water leaks and touches that body, it turns a corner.
那水泄流來碰到那個體它就拐彎了
won't rush to the village
就不會沖到村莊
So this is predictable
所以這個可以預測
predictable
可以預知啦
Then make some preparations for evacuation
然後做一些避難的一些準備
So Japan has done a lot in this regard
所以日本在這方面做了非常多
Thanks
謝謝
i want to end
我想在結束之前
Let us know about our August
待會預告一下我們8月份
Feast of knowledge next month
下個月的知識饗宴
by Chen Zhicheng
是由陳志成研究員
is the biomedical
是本院生物醫學
Institute of Science
科學研究所
What's the matter with soreness?
要主講的是酸痛是怎麼回事
So this is a life science subject
所以這是一個生命科學的題材
talk about pain slowly
要慢慢談痛覺
molecular biology
分子生物學
receptor molecule with acid
與酸的受體分子
that's there
那在
before we all get ready to leave
我們大家準備離開之前
let us once again warmly
讓我們再度以熱烈的
Thank you for your wonderful speech today
掌聲謝謝今天的精彩演講
Thank you all for coming
謝謝大家的光臨
thank you all
謝謝大家
Related here, is any of the said related.
Yn ymwneud yma, yw'r unrhyw o'r ddweud yn ymwneud.